{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man's opinion in Barron v. Baltimore refused to apply Bill of Rights protections to state\ngovernments. He was the target of Andrew Jackson's derisive remark \"now let him enforce it,\"\nand he asserted his Court's power in a case about \"midnight appointments.\" For 10 points, name\nthis Chief Justice whose ruling in Marbury v. Madison asserted the power of judicial review.",
      "answer": "John Marshall, Marshall"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pope Leo I convinced Attila the Hun not to perform this kind of action. This kind of action\nwas done by Gauls following the 390 BC Battle of the Allia. In 410 AD, Alaric led an army of\nVisigoths in performing this action, which St. Jerome identified as the effective end of the\nEmpire. For 10 points, identify this action in which the \"eternal city\" is pillaged.",
      "answer": "sack of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "The formation of this institution triggered the Key West Agreement on its proper usage, which\nwas negotiated on its behalf by its first secretary, Stuart Symington. This organization conducted\nProject Blue Book, a study of UFOs, and it operates Area 51. For 10 points, name this branch of\nthe US military which operates B-52s, F-16s, and other fighter jets.",
      "answer": "United States Air Force, Air Force, USAF"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1970, the concluding game of this event featured the dramatic entrance of an injured Willis\nReed. This event included the \"flu game\" in 1997 and an upset in 2011 that put a championship\nin the hands of Jason Terry, Shawn Marion, and Dirk Nowitski. For 10 points, name this annual\nJune event, which awards the Larry O'Brien trophy to teams such as the Bulls, Heat, or Lakers.",
      "answer": "the NBA Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country's banks, which had been largely taken over by Russian organized criminals by\n2013, underwent a savings account \"haircut.\" This country’s \"enosis\" (pr. ee-NOH-siss)\nmovement propelled Archbishop Makarios to power, sparking an invasion that still divides this\nisland. For 10 points, name this country with Greek and Turkish sectors on an island.",
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This instrument was invented by a Belgian seeking a solution to the problem of clarinets\nraising their pitch when overblown. This instrument was played by Cannonball Adderley as well\nas the composer of Giant Steps, John Coltrane. For 10 points, name this classical and jazz\ninstrument which has alto and tenor varieties and is a woodwind made out of brass.",
      "answer": "saxophone, sax"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1985, this company sued Minolta over the distinctive crossed letters in its logo. This\ncompany is the descendent of Standard Oil of New Jersey, and it employed Joseph Hazelwood,\nwho was accused of being responsible for a 1989 disaster on Prince William Sound. For 10\npoints, name this company whose Valdez tanker caused a huge oil spill, eleven years before it\nmerged with Mobil.",
      "answer": "Exxon, Exxon Mobil Corporation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first Church council named for this place endorsed ultramontanism and espoused the\ndoctrine of Papal infallibility. The second council named for this place introduced the vernacular\nmass and renounced anti-Semitism. For 10 points, identify this namesake of 1868 and 1962\nCatholic ecumenical councils, which is also the independent state where the Pope lives.",
      "answer": "Vatican, Vatican City"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man refused to continue working on the film The Golden Age after denouncing his\ncollaborator, Luis Buñuel, for \"communism and atheism,\" three years after he completed Un\nChien Andalou (pr. uh shee-EN on-da-LOO) For 10 points, name this Spanish surrealist who\npainted The Persistence of Memory, which shows several melting watches.",
      "answer": "Salvador Dali, Dali"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nobility serving under this dynasty followed the \"Table of Ranks\" to determine bureaucratic\nadvancement. This royal house came to power after three different \"False Dmitris\" were\nsuppressed during the Time of Troubles. For 10 points, name this house founded by Mikhail I in\n1613, which remained in control of Russia until the twentieth century.",
      "answer": "Romanov, Romanov Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) Whose nomination as Walter Mondale's running mate in 1984 made her the first\nwoman to be a major-party U.S. Vice-Presidential candidate?",
      "answer": "Geraldine Ferraro, Ferraro"
    },
    {
      "question": "The city of Bagram was originally the capital of an ethnically Greek state that practiced this\nreligion. Two statues of this religion's founder at Bamiyan (pr. BAY-mee-yahn) were destroyed\nby the Taliban. For 10 points, name this religion whose Vajryana (pr. VAHJ-rye-AH-nuh) form\nis practiced in Tibet by followers of the Dalai Lama.",
      "answer": "Buddhism"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of his life, this man gave a speech identifying the \"three boxes\" as the source of\nrights. This man was nominated for Vice-President by the Equal Rights Party on the Victoria\nWoodhull ticket. This orator gave a speech asking \"what, to the slave, is the Fourth of July\" after\nfounding The North Star. This author of My Bondage and My Freedom wrote about his escape\nfrom Mr. Covey in Maryland. For 10 points, name this former slave turned abolitionist.",
      "answer": "Frederick Douglass, Douglass"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with Henry David Thoreau, this thinker was cited as the chief Western influence on\nGandhi. His pacifist tome The Kingdom of God is Within You made him the leader of dissenting\nChristians in early twentieth century Russia. For 10 points, name this man who viewed his\ntheological work as more important than his novels, such as Anna Karenina",
      "answer": "Leo Tolstoy, Tolstoy, Lev Nikolayevich Tolstoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was set in motion when Abel Corbin introduced its two plotters to the President,\nand Daniel Butterfield agreed to pass along inside information. This 1869 event tainted the Grant\nadministration and was an attempt by James Fisk and Jay Gould to \"corner\" the gold market. For\n10 points, identify this day, which shares its name with a post-Thanksgiving shopping event.",
      "answer": "Black Friday"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king ordered the destruction of all remaining Protestant churches in the Edict of\nFontainebleau (pr. FAHN-tohn-blow). He was opposed at his accession by the Fronde\nmovement, which was countered by his early advisor, Cardinal Mazarin. For 10 points, name this\nmonarch who reigned for seventy-two years as the absolutist \"Sun King\" of France.",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man headed the Firebird and GTO projects while he was chief engineer of Pontiac, prior\nto starting his own namesake company. In 1982, he was arrested for participating in a cocaine\ndeal, which he was acquitted of at trial after arguing entrapment. For 10 points, identify this man\nwhose car firm produced a gull-winged, unpainted steel car used in Back to the Future.",
      "answer": "John DeLorean, DeLorean"
    },
    {
      "question": "This party was victimized by the Zinoviev letter hoax, which purported to show Soviet control\nof its operations and brought down its first prime minister, Ramsay Macdonald. This party was\nfirst represented in Parliament by Scottish coal miner Keir Hardie. For 10 points, name this\nparty, now the more left-wing of the two largest political parties in the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": "Labour Party, Labour"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zacharias Janssen may have invented the first version of this device, which was first used in\nbiology by Anton van Leeuwenhoek (pr. LAY-ven-hoke). In 1932, Ernst Ruska pioneered the\n\"electron\" type of this device, which was used to discover cells in cork by Robert Hooke. For 10\npoints, identify this device which lens-grinders created to peer at tiny objects.",
      "answer": "microscope"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's prominent depiction on the cover of When the Word Is Given offended his\nsuperiors, as did his commentary that the John F. Kennedy assassination was \"a case of chickens\ncoming home to roost.\" He was killed at the Audubon Ballroom, most likely by agents of Elijah\nMuhammad. For 10 points, name this chief spokesman for the Nation of Islam.",
      "answer": "Malcom X, Malcolm Little, Little"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the autumn of 1649, this man led armies which sacked Drogheda (pr. DRAH-huh-dah),\nleading to his reputation as a cruel conqueror of Ireland. He was succeeded by his son Richard\nafter his death. For 10 points, name this leader of the New Model Army who attained supreme\npower as \"Lord Protector of England\" after the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell, Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) What President of Germany, who appointed Hitler Chancellor in 1933, was the\nnamesake of a zeppelin that caught fire above New Jersey in 1937?",
      "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg, Hindenburg"
    },
    {
      "question": "When applied to an entire country, this process is known as an \"interdict,\" which was notably\nused against England under King John. This process was applied to Holy Roman Emperor Henry\nIV, who had to kneel in the snow at Canossa to have it reversed by Pope Gregory VII. For 10\npoints, identify this process of withholding sacraments from a person who has offended Catholic\nlaw.",
      "answer": "excommunication"
    },
    {
      "question": "Albert Gallatin attempted to calm the Mingo Creek Association during this event, which was\nsuppressed by the \"Watermelon Army\" led by Light Horse Harry Lee. Sitting President George\nWashington personally rode out against this event in 1794. For 10 points, name this Western\nPennsylvania uprising against a new excise tax on liquor.",
      "answer": "Whiskey Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting by this man was ordered defaced by the Council of Trent, leading to the man who\naltered his work being known as \"The Breeches-Painter.\" Daniele da Volterra added loincloths to\ncover the nudity in this man's The Last Judgment. For 10 points, name this painter who worked\nlying on his back on a scaffold to decorate the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.",
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo",
        "Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An attempt to fly this country's flag at an American school here led to the \"Martyrs' Day\" riot.\nThis country's dictator Omar Torrijos (toh-REE-hoce) signed a treaty with Jimmy Carter that gave\nthis country control over a formerly extraterritorial \"zone.\" For 10 points, name this country which\nthe U.S. encouraged to declare independence from Colombia in order to build a canal.",
      "answer": "Panama"
    },
    {
      "question": "George Taylor opened a mill to produce this good in a way that satisfied Quakers affiliated with\nthe Free Produce Movement. Slaves in tobacco fields dreaded being \"sold down the river\" to work\nwith this good. For 10 points, name this good produced in the Deep South, which became\neconomically feasible again after Eli Whitney invented its \"gin.\"",
      "answer": "cotton"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state was where Teddy Roosevelt once suffered an economic setback as a rancher, though\ntoday it’s the site of Theodore Roosevelt National Park. This state’s economy has recently boomed\ndue to lucrative oil wells around its city of Williston. For 10 points, name this state whose capital\nwas named to attract German immigrants, and which was depicted in the 1990’s film Fargo.",
      "answer": "North Dakota"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of this decade, the Mayerling scandal erupted. During this decade, Chinese Gordon\nwas killed fighting the Mahdi in Sudan. The rules for colonialism were set out at the Berlin\nConference during this decade. For 10 points, identify this decade in which Queen Victoria\ncelebrated the Golden Jubilee of her 1837 accession to the throne.",
      "answer": [
        "1880s",
        "1880"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man secured recognition of independence at the Treaty of Lausanne, which ended the\ndeportation of his country's Greek minority. This founder of the Republican People's Party banned\nthe wearing of fezzes and introduced the Latin alphabet as part of the \"Six Arrows\" platform. For\n10 points, name this founder of modern secular Turkey.",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal",
        "Kemal",
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "Ataturk"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author fictionalized Vice-President Aaron Burr in her novel The Minister's Wooing and\ndepicted fugitives in the Great Dismal Swamp in Dred. She wrote a \"key to\" her major novel,\nwhich led Abraham Lincoln to describe her as \"the little lady who started this big war.\" For 10\npoints, name this author who created Simon Legree in the anti-slavery book Uncle Tom's Cabin.",
      "answer": [
        "Harriet Beecher Stowe",
        "Stowe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Cincinnati's George Remus made his fortune in this activity, possibly inspiring the title\ncharacter of The Great Gatsby. An urban legend stating that the Kennedy family originally made\nits fortune in this activity is based on the testimony of Frank Costello, one of many mobsters\ninvolved in it. For 10 points, what was this activity of smuggling alcohol during Prohibition?",
      "answer": [
        "bootlegging",
        "rumrunning"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What city defeated Genoa (in the Chioggia (pr. kee-OH-juh) War and grew into a great\nmaritime power under the leadership of \"doges?\"",
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man commanded the construction of Fort St. Simon during a 1742 Spanish raid on his\ncolony. This man, who transported Methodist founder John Wesley to America, acquired land\nfrom Tomochici and founded Savannah. For 10 points, name this English colonist who created a\nhaven for debtors called Georgia.",
      "answer": [
        "James Oglethorpe",
        "Oglethorpe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A prominent player of this instrument was surreptitiously recorded on the obscene \"Bus\nTapes.\" Jo Jones played this instrument in the Count Basie Orchestra, and it was played by the\nleader of the Jazz Messengers, Art Blakey. For 10 points, name this jazz instrument played by\nJoe Morello of the Dave Brubeck Quartet, Max Roach and Buddy Rich, who used sticks while\nplaying.",
      "answer": [
        "drums",
        "drum"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a painting by this artist, Ambrosio de Spinola receives the keys to a besieged Dutch town\nfrom Justin of Nassau. This artist of The Surrender of Breda also painted The Rokeby Venus. A\ndwarf in a dress is one of the title attendants of the Infanta Margarita in a painting by this artist.\nFor 10 points, name this Spanish artist of Las Meninas.",
      "answer": [
        "Diego Velazquez",
        "Velazquez",
        "Diego Rodriguez de Silva y Velazquez"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to legend, Horatio Nelson’s body was stored in this substance after the Battle of\nTrafalgar. This product was created as a way to dispose of the molasses created as a byproduct of\nthe manufacture of sugar in the Caribbean. In the British Navy, Edward Vernon created the\npractice of diluting this substance with water. For 10 points, name this component of grog.",
      "answer": "rum"
    },
    {
      "question": "This movement's \"first lady\" recorded \"Don't Sleep in the Subway\" and \"Downtown.\" Another\nact from this period, which sang \"Doo Wah Diddy,\" was Manfred Mann's Earth Band. This mid1960s movement included the Dave Clark Five, The Troggs, The Animals, as well as The\nRolling Stones. For 10 points, name this wave of England-based artists who achieved American\npopularity.",
      "answer": "British Invasion"
    },
    {
      "question": "This route's eastern half was used by people who split off onto the Mormon or Bozeman paths\ninstead of finishing this route. This route existed for twenty-five years before it became suitable\nfor wagon usage as far as Fort Hall. At the end of its use, it went all the way to the Willamette\nValley. For 10 points, name this iconic route used by settlers to the Pacific Northwest.",
      "answer": "Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man forced Gustavo Leigh out of his government for demanding a date for transition to\ndemocracy. This man came to power after his predecessor nationalized the copper industry, and\nwhile in power he relied on a group of economic advisors called the Chicago Boys. For 10\npoints, name this dictator who overthrew Salvador Allende to take control of Chile.",
      "answer": [
        "Augusto Pinochet",
        "Pinochet",
        "Augusto Jose Ramon Pinochet Ugarte"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Kicking Bear added a sacred article of clothing to this movement that was possibly modeled\non the temple garments of Mormons. This movement, which wore supposedly bulletproof shirts,\nwas founded by Wodziwob and popularized by Wovoka. For 10 points, identify this religious\nand social movement of 1890s Plains Indians whose practitioners were killed at Wounded Knee.",
      "answer": "Ghost Dance"
    },
    {
      "question": "U.S. doctors worked with a dictator of this country to eradicate yaws. This country was\nevacuated by U.S. troops as the major effect of Franklin Roosevelt's \"good neighbor\" policy;\nRoosevelt claimed to have written this country's constitution. For 10 points, name this country\nwhere the U.S. intervened in 1994 to restore Jean-Bertrand Aristide to Port-au-Prince.",
      "answer": "Haiti"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author corresponded with Colonel Thomas Wentworth Higginson during the Civil War,\nwhich was the subject of her poem \"It Feels a Shame to Be Alive.\" She described a carriage\ncontaining \"eternity\" in another poem. For 10 points, name this \"belle of Amherst\" whose poems\nsuch as \"Because I Could Not Stop for Death\" were published only after her death.",
      "answer": [
        "Emily Dickinson",
        "Dickinson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Russian tsar freed the serfs in 1861 and was assassinated twenty years later?",
      "answer": "Alexander II"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once walked all the way across Virginia lengthwise to secure a promised spot in\ncollege at Hampton. He promised to keep \"as separate as the five fingers on each hand\" and\nadvocated that his followers \"cast down your bucket where you are.\" For 10 points, name this\nman whose Atlanta Compromise speech staked out a moderate civil rights position in 1895.",
      "answer": [
        "Booker T. Washington",
        "Washington"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Early objects created using this device are called incunabula. This device was introduced to\nVenice by Aldus Manutius and brought to England by William Caxton. A goldsmith from Mainz\nused a screw-press for his \"movable-type\" version of this device. For 10 points, name this device\nfirst created in the West by Johannes Gutenberg.",
      "answer": "printing press"
    },
    {
      "question": "Between political offices, this man was a law partner of future FCC commissioner Newton\nMinnow. This man snapped \"don't wait for the translation\" at Valerin Zorin during his time as\nU.S. ambassador to the United Nations. He was dubbed \"egghead\" during his two failed\nPresidential runs. For 10 points, name this man who lost twice to Dwight Eisenhower.",
      "answer": [
        "Adlai Stevenson",
        "Stevenson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was once marooned on Bermuda in the wreck of the Sea Venture. He created the\nOrinoco cultivar of a product that he put into four barels during his return to England, where he\npresented his wife, under the new name \"Rebecca,\" to the royal court. For 10 points, name this\nhusband of Pocahontas who devised the financially viable form of American tobacco.",
      "answer": [
        "John Rolfe",
        "Rolfe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1861, Johann Reis arguably accomplished this task by making use of magneto-restriction.\nElisha Gray claimed to have accomplished this task, though he lost out on a patent to the man\nwho is generally credited with this accomplishment and used the result to transmit, \"Watson,\ncome here, I want you.\" For 10 points, name this achievement of Alexander Graham Bell.",
      "answer": [
        "inventing the telephone",
        "telephone"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "President-in-waiting Luis Donaldo Colosio was assassinated in this city in 1994. This city's\nAvenida Revolución (ah-veh-NEE-duh reh-voh-loo-see-OWN) was the location of Cesar\nCardini's restaurant, where the Caesar salad was invented. For 10 points, name this city in Baja\nCalifornia which attracts numerous American tourists from nearby San Diego.",
      "answer": "Tijuana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city constructed a paved road used to transport boats overland called the Diolkos. A\ndispute between this city and its colony of Corcyra was a cause of the Peloponnesian War.\nCypselid rulers of this city included its second tyrant, Periander. Capitals bedecked with\nacanthus leaves characterized this city’s namesake order of columns. For 10 points, name this\nancient Greek city located on a namesake isthmus.",
      "answer": [
        "Corinth",
        "Korinthos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem which became a protest song about this activity compares the \"scent of magnolias,\nsweet and fresh\" to the \"sudden smell of burning flesh.\" Federal attempts to crack down on this\npractice included the Dyer Bill. Ida B. Wells was an activist against this practice, which is the\nsubject of \"Strange Fruit.\" For 10 points, identify this practice of extrajudicial mob killings of\nblacks.",
      "answer": [
        "lynchings",
        "lynching"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this title boasted that his descendants would rule for 10,000 generations, though\ncounting him they ruled for only two. That holder of this title followed Legalist precepts while\nburning subversive books and died after taking mercury pills in search of immortality. For 10\npoints, name this title taken by Qin Shi Huang and later used by leaders of the Han dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "emperor of China",
        "huangdi",
        "di"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader forcibly dismissed the Rump Parliament and replaced it with Barebone’s\nparliament. He was hated in Ireland for atrocities committed at Wexford and Drogheda. He\nhelped win the Battle of Naseby as a cavalry commander in the New Model Army. For 10 points,\nname this man who served as Lord Protector of England in the interregnum following the\nexecution of Charles I of England.",
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Cromwell",
        "Cromwell"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The Trung Sisters are national heroes of what Southeast Asian country's resistance to\nChinese occupation?",
      "answer": "Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern-day country was outraged by the Council of Blood being imposed as its ruler, as\nwell as by the Tenth Penny tax. It allied with the \"Sea Beggars\" against Spanish governors such\nas the Duke of Alba and won its independence in the Eighty Years War. For 10 points, name this\ncountry where William the Silent reigned over land reclaimed from the sea via dikes.",
      "answer": [
        "the Netherlands",
        "Holland",
        "the United Provinces"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman was implicated in a fraud known as the Affair of the Diamond Necklace. She\nbecame known as \"the widow Capet\" following the death of her husband, Louis XVI. For 10\npoints, name this queen of France who legendarily dismissed a crowd of peasants crying out for\nbread by saying \"let them eat cake.\"",
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people believed that people who died by drowning went to an underworld ruled by\nTlaloc (pr. tuh-LAH-lock) rather than the main underworld, Mictlan (pr. MIKT-lon). These\npeople believed that an eagle with a snake in its mouth had alighted on a cactus, telling them\nwhere to build their capital. For 10 points, name this group that worshipped Quetzalcoatl (pr.\nKET-sul-coh-AH-tul).",
      "answer": [
        "Aztecs",
        "Aztec"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A sculpture group by this artist depicts an incident in which Eustache de Saint Pierre led six\nmen into captivity in 1347 following a battle with Edward III. The most iconic piece by this\nsculptor was part of his exhibition The Gates of Hell and represents Dante planning the Divine\nComedy. For 10 points, name this sculptor of The Burghers of Calais and The Thinker.",
      "answer": [
        "Auguste Rodin",
        "Rodin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This industry became involved in a scandal during the Spanish-American War when it\nsupplied poor-quality goods to Nelson Miles's troops in Puerto Rico. This industry was later\nfictionalized as mistreating immigrant Jurgis Rudkus, leading Theodore Roosevelt to support the\nPure Food and Drug Act. For 10 points, name this industry which Upton Sinclair targeted in The\nJungle.",
      "answer": [
        "meatpacking industry",
        "meat"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two sports teams based in this country met in the Naismith Cup. In 1993, a team based in this\ncountry employed John Olerud and Paul Molitor. This country's lesser-known national sport is\nlacrosse, and its football league contests the Grey Cup every year. For 10 points, name this\nformer home of the NBA's Grizzlies and current home of baseball's Blue Jays.",
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man personally financed and organized a rescue mission for employees of Electronic\nData Systems who were imprisoned in Iran. He chose James Stockdale as his running mate in a\nPresidential election that saw him widely mocked for buying network airtime to display a series\nof charts. For 10 points, name this independent who received twenty percent of the vote in 1992.",
      "answer": [
        "H. Ross Perot",
        "Perot",
        "Hiriam Ross Perot"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Emmanuel Timoni first described a method of preventing this disease, which Mary Worley\nMontagu famously was guarded against in Constantinople. Cotton Mather wrote in support of\ninoculation against this disease, which was proved feasible in England by Edward Jenner. For 10\npoints, name this formerly devastating disease which was eliminated by the 1990s.",
      "answer": "smallpox"
    },
    {
      "question": "The chief justice during this event, William Stoughton, controversially allowed \"spectral\nevidence\" to be introduced, an action later condemned by Increase Mather. These events began\nwith accusations against the slave Tituba and resulted in dozens of executions by hanging and\npressing. For 10 points, name this episode of mass hysteria in 1692 Massachusetts.",
      "answer": "Salem witch trials"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of the groundwork for this institution was laid at the San Francisco Conference by spy\nAlger Hiss. At this institution, Valerian Zorin was told “don’t wait for the translation” by Adlai\nStevenson, who served as U.S. ambassador to this institution under John F. Kennedy. For 10\npoints, name this successor to the League of Nations which meets in New York.",
      "answer": [
        "the UN",
        "United Nations"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The Qing Dynasty was founded by what ethnic group from the north of China, which\nmandated that all Han Chinese wear their hair in queues?",
      "answer": [
        "Manchus",
        "Manchu",
        "Manchurians",
        "Manchurian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The men's section of this event was dominated by Bill Rodgers in the 1970s. In 1980, Rosie\nRuiz was disqualified from this event after initially \"winning\" its women's title by taking\nshortcuts. From 2002 to 2013, all men's winners of this event were from either Kenya or\nEthiopia. For 10 points, name this distance running event which, in 2013, was attacked by\nterrorists.",
      "answer": [
        "Boston Marathon",
        "New York Marathon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's fictitious sister Judith is hypothesized to make a point about women writers in\nVirginia Woolf's A Room of One's Own. This man left only his \"second-best bed\" to his widow\nAnne Hathaway, but did leave women such roles as Cordelia, Beatrice, and Ophelia. For 10\npoints, name this author of King Lear, Much Ado About Nothing, and Hamlet.",
      "answer": [
        "William Shakespeare",
        "Shakespeare"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Schoolgirl Venetia Burney proposed what is now the official name of this object. This body\nwas discovered in 1930 using the blink comparator machine by Vesto Slipher's new apprentice,\nClyde Tombaugh. In 2006, this object was demoted by the International Astronomical Union to\n\"dwarf planet\" status. For 10 points, name this trans-Neptunian object and former ninth planet.",
      "answer": "Pluto"
    },
    {
      "question": "Peter Shann Ford has attempted to prove, using acoustic analysis, that this man did not flub a\nline that had been scripted for him. This man indicated that \"the Eagle has landed\" while on a\nmission with Michael Collins and Buzz Aldrin. For 10 points, name this commander of Apollo\n11 who said \"one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind\" as he took the first step onto\nthe Moon.",
      "answer": [
        "Neil Armstrong",
        "Armstrong"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to this religion, a compass-like device called the Liahona (pr. LEE-uh-HOH-nuh)\nwas used to show an escape route from Jerusalem. Other artifacts of this religion include Urim\nand Thummim, the \"seer stones\" used to translate the golden plates which the angel Moroni\nrevealed to its founder. For 10 points, name this church founded by Joseph Smith.",
      "answer": [
        "Mormon church",
        "LDS",
        "Latter-Day Saints"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city once turned away foreign help during an earthquake in fear of contaminating its\nsocial system, which involved events such as the \"krypteia\" (pr. crip-TAY-uh), a ritual\ndeclaration of war on its slave class, the helots (pr. HELL-ots). For 10 points, name this city\nwhere two lines of kings oversaw the cultivation of boys from age seven into full-time soldiers.",
      "answer": "Sparta"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Council of Trent mandated that Catholic realms adopt this standard, which did not arrive\nin Greece until 1923. It replaced an earlier standard named for Julius Caesar. When it was\nintroduced to Great Britain in 1751, monthly debtors cried \"give us back our eleven days.\" For\n10 points, identify this modern calendar named for the Pope who devised it.",
      "answer": [
        "Gregorian calendar",
        "Gregorian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "American \"shows\" described by this word featured stock characters such as Mr. Bones and\nperformers dressed in blackface. In the middle ages, this word generally described people such as\nminnesingers (pr. MIN-eh-singers) and troubadours, who sang or played the harp, flute, or lute.\nFor 10 points, name these people who were travelling musicians of the middle ages.",
      "answer": [
        "minstrels",
        "minstrel"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Southern supporters of this man launched racist attacks on his opponent by claiming that this\nman's rival danced with Mary Booze. This man became president of the firm constructing the\nEmpire State Building after losing the 1928 Presidential election to Herbert Hoover. For 10\npoints, name this \"Happy Warrior,\" the first major-party Catholic candidate.",
      "answer": [
        "Al Smith",
        "Smith"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person was appointed as the head of an expedition to Scutari (pr. scoo-TAH-ree) by\nwar minister Sidney Herbert, who knew of her efforts to improve sanitation. She became known\nas the \"Lady with the Lamp\" for her efforts during the Crimean War. For 10 points, name this\n1850s British woman, the founder of modern nursing.",
      "answer": [
        "Florence Nightingale",
        "Nightingale"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(EXAMPLE BONUS QUESTION) Japan underwent an internal political crisis over invading Korea in the Seikanron, a\ncomponent of what larger movement to modernize Japan and replace the Tokugawa shogunate\nwith a constitutional monarchy?",
      "answer": "the Meiji Restoration"
    },
    {
      "question": "The events at this location became widely known fifty years later thanks to a book by Stuart\nLake. The incident here resulted in the death of Tom and Frank McLaury as well as Billy\nClanton, though the \"law\" side suffered no casualties among Doc Holliday or Wyatt Earp. For 10\npoints, name this place in Tombstone, Arizona where an 1881 \"shootout\" took place.",
      "answer": "the O.K. Corral"
    },
    {
      "question": "The proposal to join this body was opposed in the Lodge Reservations, which specifically\nobjected to Article X (ten) of its charter, committing all members to repel any aggression against\none. William Borah's Irreconcilables movement drummed up public resistance to American\nparticipation in this organization. For 10 points, name this ineffective international body created\nby the Treaty of Versailles, which the U.S. never joined despite Woodrow Wilson's protestations.",
      "answer": "League of Nations"
    },
    {
      "question": "Following Ross Perot's most successful attempt at the Presidency, Perot embarked on a\ncampaign against this legislation, predicting it would cause a \"giant sucking sound.\" This\nlegislation was championed in a televised debate by Al Gore, and its architects included Carlos\nSalinas and Brian Mulroney. For 10 points, name this continental trade pact.",
      "answer": [
        "NAFTA",
        "North American Free Trade Agreement"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man launched the anti-hunger Operation Breadbasket as a project of his\n\"Rainbow/PUSH\" coalition. In the 1980s, he ran for the Democratic Presidential nomination\ntwice and was dogged by reports of anti-Semitism during the New York primary. For 10 points,\nname this former confidante of Martin Luther King, Jr. who became a prominent civil rights\nspokesman.",
      "answer": [
        "Jesse Jackson",
        "Jackson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When it became apparent that this event had failed, a disgusted Erich Ludendorff simply\nwalked away, leading its main organizer to be sentenced to the Landsberg, where Mein Kampf\nwas written. For 10 points, name this failed 1923 attempt by Adolf Hitler to seize power in\nGermany by leading an uprising at a Munich drinking venue.",
      "answer": "Beer Hall Putsch"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's great-grandfather raised the 1st Mississippi Partisan Rangers in the Civil War and\nwrote The White Rose of Memphis. This author used that ancestor as the model for the\nprotagonist of The Unvanquished, Colonel Sartoris. For 10 points, name this Mississippi-born\nnovelist of \"A Rose for Emily\" and The Sound and the Fury.",
      "answer": "William Faulkner, Faulkner"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man said he planned to use a Kärcher pressure-washer to \"clean out\" suburbs. In 2014,\nthis former leader of the UMP was questioned by police for alleged corruption in a judicial\nappointment in Monaco. He lost a close re-election bid in 2012 to his left-wing rival François\nHollande (pr. frah-SWAH oh-LAHND). For 10 points, name this former President of France.",
      "answer": [
        "Nicolas Sarkozy",
        "Sarkozy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Florida developer Henry Flagler got rich as a business partner of this man. Frederick Taylor\nGates advised him on how to direct his philanthropy, which included providing the startup funds\nfor Spelman College and the University of Chicago. For 10 points, name this businessman who\nwas attacked by Ida Tarbell as a monopolist after founding Standard Oil.",
      "answer": [
        "John D. Rockefeller",
        "Rockefeller",
        "John Davison Rockefeller Sr."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2014, a Senate candidate from this state was criticized for posting graphic X-rays on his\nwebsite; that second cousin of Barack Obama, Milton Wolf, failed to win the Republican\nnomination here. This state is where independent Greg Orman is seeking to unseat incumbent Pat\nRoberts. For 10 points, name this state governed by Sam Brownback from Topeka.",
      "answer": "Kansas"
    },
    {
      "question": "An early practitioner of this art form was satirized as \"elevating\" it from a hot-air balloon in\nan engraving by Honoré Daumier (pr. oh-no-RAY dow-mee-EY). This art form was used to\ndepict The Steerage by Alfred Stieglitz and Moon and Half Dome by a later American leader of\nf/64 (\"eff sixty-four\"). For 10 points, name this art form used by Ansel Adams to produce prints.",
      "answer": "photography"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The \"condottiere\" (pr. cahn-DOE-tee-AIR-ee) were what type of soldiers, who fought\nmost of the wars of Renaissance Italy and were often of English origin and whose use was\nwarned against by Machiavelli?",
      "answer": "mercenaries"
    },
    {
      "question": "The process of creating these places was paused after the article \"Dizzy From Success.\" The\nattempt to bring the entire countryside into these places resulted in the Holodomor and other\nepisodes of famine, as well as direct killings of alleged \"kulaks.\" For 10 points, the First Five Year Plan was aimed at transforming all Soviet agriculture into what socialist institutions?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet collective farms",
        "collective farms",
        "sovkhoz",
        "kolkhoz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer was patronized by Cardinal Rudolf of Austria, to whom he dedicated his\nArchduke Trio. This composer wrapped his head in pillows and hid in a basement during the\nBattle of Wagram, attempting to protect what little hearing he had left. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer of the Pastoral and Choral symphonies as well as \"Fur Elise.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Ludwig van Beethoven",
        "Beethoven"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Following controversy over his proposed \"budget repair bill,\" this man defeated Tom Barrett\nfor the second time in two years. An occupation of his state capitol occurred after he planned to\noutlaw bargaining with public unions, leading to a recall election which he survived in 2012. For\n10 points, name this Republican governor of Wisconsin.",
      "answer": [
        "Scott Walker",
        "Walker"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician controversially claimed that this place is not independent due to \"money and\nethnic votes.\" This place was to be recognized as a \"distinct society\" in a failed 1987\namendment block, the Meech Lake Accord. This place rejected independence by a narrow\nmargin in a 1995 referendum. For 10 points, name this French-speaking Canadian province.",
      "answer": "Quebec"
    },
    {
      "question": "A powerful advisor based in this city uncovered the Tavora (tuh-VORE-uh) Conspiracy. This\ncity, where the Marquis of Pombal came to power, was the location of a 1755 disaster that\ninspired philosophers across Europe to ask how God could allow large-scale death. For 10\npoints, name this city that was devastated by a large earthquake described in Candide.",
      "answer": "Lisbon"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ran for governor of Massachusetts in 1852 on the Free Soil ticket, and did not accept\nan offer to become president of Antioch College until the election returns confirmed his loss. He\nwent on a tour of Prussia in 1843, six years after joining the U.S.'s first state board of education.\nFor 10 points, name this \"father of the common school,\" a leading educational reformer.",
      "answer": [
        "Horace Mann",
        "Mann"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ship never fought a major battle, as it was under upgrades during Jutland (YUT-land).\nThis ship was designed at the behest of First Sea Lord Jacky Fisher and targeted in a namesake\n\"hoax\" by Virginia Woolf, who pretended to be an Ethiopian princess. For 10 points, name this\nship whose construction spurred a battleship \"arms race\" in the decade before World War I.",
      "answer": [
        "HMS Dreadnought",
        "Dreadnought"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This company helped put Butterfield's stagecoach line out of business despite operating for\nonly eighteen months. It went as far west as Sacramento from its origin at St. Joseph, Missouri,\nand employed those who answered an ad for \"young, skinny, wiry fellows not over eighteen.\"\nFor 10 points, name this 1860 to 1861 venture for delivering mail using a network of animals.",
      "answer": "Pony Express"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, the preacher John Ball posed the riddle “When Adam delve and Eve span,\nwho was then the gentleman?” This event ended shortly after William Walworth, the mayor of\nLondon, beheaded its leader. This event targeted Richard II and protested the recent poll tax. For\n10 points, name this 1381 uprising in England led by Wat Tyler among a class of people.",
      "answer": "the Peasants' Revolt"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people displaced an Iron Age culture known as the Villanovans. These people\nworshipped gods including Tin, Uni, and Cel, and they spoke a now-lost language whose last\nknown speaker was the Roman emperor Claudius. They legendarily provided the final three\nkings of Rome. For 10 points, name these pre-Roman inhabitants of the central Italian peninsula.",
      "answer": [
        "Etruscans",
        "Etruscan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Todor Zhivkov was the longtime Communist dictator of what Eastern European\ncountry, which used ricin pellets fired out of a modified umbrella to assassinate dissidents, and\nroughly corresponds to ancient Thrace?",
      "answer": "Bulgaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This denomination was wracked by the Landmarkism controversy in the 1850s, shortly after it\nwas founded under the leadership of William Bullein Johnson. This denomination split off over\nthe refusal of the Home Mission Society to appoint slaveholders as missionaries. For 10 points,\nname this largest Protestant denomination in the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Southern Baptist Convention",
        "Southern Baptist",
        "Southern Baptism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The admirals who worked for this man included Gil Eanes (ee-AH-nesh) and Antonio Noli.\nHis capture of Ceuta (say-OO-tuh) and leadership of the Order of Christ gave him vast\ndisposable funds, which he used to create the first map that extended to Cape Bojador (boh-hahDOR). For 10 points, name this member of the Aviz Dynasty who never ascended to the\nPortuguese throne but left his mark as a patron of expeditions at the start of the Age of\nExploration.",
      "answer": [
        "Prince Henry the Navigator",
        "Henry the Navigator"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's reforms were sabotaged when Qi (pr. CHEE) sent dancing girls and horses to\ndistract the Duke of Lu. This man advocated the \"reification (pr. RAY-iff-uh-CAY-shun) of\nnames\" and the \"five relationships.\" For 10 points, name this author of the \"Five Classics\" whose\nsayings, collected in the Analects, form the basis of a traditional Chinese ruling philosophy.",
        "answer": "Confucius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Confucius lived during the Spring and Autumn period, in which what Chinese dynasty,\nnominally in power from 1046 to 256 BC, was in decline?",
        "answer": "Eastern Zhou, Zhou, Zhou Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the Ottoman Empire's Tulip Period began with the Treaty of Passarowitz\n(pr. puh-SAH-roe-vits). At the end of this century, the White Lotus Rebellion broke out in\nChina. The Battle of Plassey and the Black Hole of Calcutta took place in this century. For 10\npoints, identify this century in which Britain took control of Canada after the French and Indian\nWar.",
        "answer": "18th, 18th century AD, 1700s, 1700"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Plassey weakened what Islamic dynasty that had ruled in India since\n1526, transferring effective control of most of India to the British East India Company?",
        "answer": "Mughal, Mughal Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Neckham first described the European use of this object, which began in 1190 after\nit was invented in China. This object was used in conjunction with Portolan charts to double the\nVenetian trading season, which previously relied on clear skies for navigation. For 10 points,\nname this navigational device which uses the Earth's magnetic field to point north.",
        "answer": "compass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other great navigational problem was solved by John Harrison with the invention\nof the \"Sea Clock\" in 1730, winning a namesake twenty-thousand pound prize?",
        "answer": "longitude, determining a ship's longitude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Ford administration declared this phenomenon \"public enemy number one\" and circulated\nbuttons which encouraged Americans to \"whip\" this thing \"now.\" Paul Volcker was instructed by\nthe Reagan administration to get this thing under control at any cost to the unemployment rate.\nFor 10 points, identify this phenomenon of generally rising prices.",
        "answer": "inflation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Volcker was the chairman of what body, a position later held by Alan Greenspan?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve, The Fed, Fed, Board of Governors, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state's Jackson County is where the Garden of Eden was located in Mormon belief. This\nstate was added to the U.S. as a slave state in exchange for Maine coming in as a free state, in its\nnamesake \"compromise.\" For 10 points, name this state that shares its name with the longest\nriver in the USA, which meets the Mississippi River here near the Gateway Arch in St. Louis.",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Missouri city of Independence was the start of what route, which settlers took to\nreach the Willamette Valley?",
        "answer": "Oregon Trail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first came to prominence by suppressing the 13 Vendémiaire (pr. VON-deem-yair)\nrebellion with what Thomas Carlyle called \"a whiff of grapeshot.\" He made his brothers Joseph\nand Jerome into the kings of Spain and Westphalia, respectively. For 10 points, name this \"First\nCounsel\" who was defeated by the Duke of Wellington at Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte, Napoleon, Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was able to remove Austria and the Holy Roman Empire from the Third\nCoalition opposing him with what great 1805 victory in what is now the Czech Republic?",
        "answer": "Austerlitz, Battle of Austerlitz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scandal leading up to this ballot question involved abusive Twitter messages sent to J.K.\nRowling. Alistair Darling appeared in an August 2014 debate on behalf of Better Together,\nwhich led the \"no\" campaign on this question. For 10 points, identify this September 2014 ballot\nquestion which sought to make Edinburgh the capital of a new sovereign country.",
        "answer": "Scottish independence, Scottish independence referendum"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which largest Scottish city by population was one of the few areas where the majority\nof people voted for independence?",
        "answer": "Glasgow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Troops who carried out this action referred to it as “Blumenkrieg”, a term meaning \"war of\nflowers,\" because they were met by cheering crowds. Kurt Schuschnigg (pr. SHOOS-neg) was\nforced to resign to clear the way for this action, which began on March 11, 1938. For 10 points,\nidentify this forced incorporation of Austria into Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "Anschluss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Austria was forbidden from unifying with Germany by the Treaty of Saint-Germain\n(pr. sahn zhair-MON), which was signed at the end of what war?",
        "answer": "World War I, First World War, the Great War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"foundations\" of this field were described in a book by David Hilbert, and its \"hyperbolic\"\nform was pioneered by János Bolyai (pr. YAH-nowsh BOWL-yai) and the Russian Nikolai\nLobachevsky (pr. LOH-buh-CHEFF-skee). For 10 points, name this math field whose\nfoundational text is the Elements by Euclid (pr. YOOK-lid), which discusses the parallel\npostulate and Pythagorean theorem.",
        "answer": "geometry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other kind of mathematics was invented simultaneously by Gottfried Leibniz and\nIsaac Newton, who long quarreled over the credit for its discovery?",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist depicted Nazi concentration camp victims in The Charnel House. In the late 1940s,\nthis wealthy artist was the primary financial backer of the French Communist Party. An earlier\npolitical painting by him shows a lightbulb, a horse, and a screaming woman in memory of a\nBasque village bombed by the Nazis. For 10 points, name this creator of Guernica.",
        "answer": "Pablo Picasso, Picasso, Pablo Ruiz y Picasso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "World War II itself caused the disappearance of many artworks, such as the Amber\nRoom formerly found in what city, which was besieged by Nazis for nine hundred days?",
        "answer": "St. Petersburg, Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s former troops revolted against it in the Mercenary War. As a result, this city's\nleader Hanno the Great was displaced by the rising Barcid dynasty, whose members included\nHamilcar and Hasdrubal. This city lost the Battle of Zama to Scipio Africanus. For 10 points\nname this ancient North African city which was defeated by Rome in three Punic Wars.",
        "answer": "Carthage"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The site of Carthage is in which present day African country, whose soccer team is\nthus known as the Carthage Eagles?",
        "answer": "Tunisia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "San Francisco 49ers, San Francisco, 49ers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "Jerry Rice, Rice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Soon after independence, this country fell under the domination of the \"hairy feet\" secret\npolice of José de Francia. This country was ruled by the eccentric Francisco Solano Lopez when\nit lost the majority of its male population to the War of the Triple Alliance. For 10 points,\nidentify this country which has developed oddly due to its landlocked position in South America.",
        "answer": "Paraguay, Republic of Paraguay, Republica del Paraguay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Triple Alliance proved a victory for Pedro II, a member of the\nBraganza Dynasty and the last person to hold what imperial title?",
        "answer": "Emperor of Brazil"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A powerful official in this government was the \"censor,\" who determined eligibility for the\nSenate. Politicians under this government followed the \"cursus honorum\" to move through the\nranks of aedile (pr. EY-dial), quaestor (pr. KWAI-stor), praetor (pr. PRAI-tor), and finally\nbecome one of two consuls. For 10 points, name this governmental system which was replaced\nby the Empire.",
        "answer": "Roman Republic, Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A legendary censor was the \"elder\" man of what name, who was also known for ending\nhis speeches in the Senate by declaring \"Carthage must be destroyed?\"",
        "answer": "Cato"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A bronze age museum is maintained at a \"crannog\" in County Clare on this island. This island\nregained its independence from Viking kingdoms at the 1014 Battle of Clontarf, re-establishing\nthe High King's seat at the hill of Tara. The Book of Kells can be seen at Trinity College Library\non this island. For 10 points, name this island, also home to the James Joyce Museum in Dublin.",
        "answer": "Ireland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What city in southwest Ireland is the namesake of a humorous poetic form?",
        "answer": "Limerick"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A desire to control this site sparked a brief 1860s war between France and Siam. This complex\nwas built by Suryavarman II (pr. SIR-yuh-VAHR-mun the second) in the early twelfth century\nand dedicated to Vishnu, though it was later used for Buddhist worship. For 10 points, identify\nthis Khmer (pr. kuh-MARE) Kingdom temple complex, or \"wat,\" in what is now Cambodia.",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat, Angkor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cambodia later came under the rule of the Khmer Rouge, a Communist movement led\nby what dictator whose original name was Saloth Sar?",
        "answer": "Pol Pot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state was the home of the \"sage of Emporia,\" Progressive activist William Allen White.\nThis state dropped the teaching of evolution from science classes in 1999. Earlier, this state was\nwhere \"Border Ruffians\" perpetrated the sack of Lawrence and were subject to the Pottawatomie\nMassacre by John Brown. For 10 points, name this state which was \"Bleeding\" in the 1850s.",
        "answer": "Kansas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Wild West town in Kansas was where Bat Masterson and Wyatt Earp served as\nlaw enforcement officers in the 1870’s?",
        "answer": "Dodge City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Argun and Ussuri rivers demarcate part of the border between these two countries. These\ntwo countries established their border in 1689 with the Treaty of Nerchinsk, which ended a brief\nconflict in the Amur River region. These two countries share a border in between Mongolia and\nKazakhstan. For 10 points, name these two geographically largest countries in Asia.",
        "answer": "Russia and China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Soviet leader's \"Secret Speech\" denouncing Stalinism was the turning point in the\nSino-Soviet split of the 1950s?",
        "answer": [
          "Nikita Khrushchev",
          "Khrushchev",
          "Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this sport, the Hershey Bears have won eleven Calder Cups. In 2014, Metallurg Magnitogorsk\nwon the Gagarin Cup as champion of a prominent European league for this sport. The top league\nin this sport awards the Hart Trophy to its MVP and the Conn Smythe Trophy to the best playoff\nperformer. For 10 points, name this sport whose champion receives the Stanley Cup.",
        "answer": [
          "ice hockey",
          "hockey"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What team, which plays at Nassau Coliseum, won four straight Stanley Cups from 1980\nto 1983?",
        "answer": [
          "New York Islanders",
          "Islanders"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Jopling wrote the standard textbook on this disease. The Greek island of Spinalonga\nonce housed people with this disease, who were treated by Marianne Cope and \"Father Damien\"\non Molokai in Hawaii. For 10 points, name this disease whose causative agent was identified in\n1873 by Gerhard Hansen, and whose sufferers were once isolated into namesake \"colonies.\"",
        "answer": "leprosy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1950, William Jopling established a leprosy hospital named after what body of water\nin the Middle East, in which lepers were instructed to bathe in the Bible?",
        "answer": [
          "Jordan River",
          "Jordan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s government organized the Congress of People’s Deputies and signed the\nIntermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. He introduced economic restructuring known as\n\"perestroika\" (pr. peh-rez-TROY-kuh) and government transparency called \"glasnost\". For 10\npoints, name this rival of Boris Yeltsin who was the final leader of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": [
          "Mikhail Gorbachev",
          "Gorbachev",
          "Mikhail Sergeyevich Gorbachev"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gorbachev ended the \"internal exile\" of what dissenting physicist, the inventor of the\nSoviet hydrogen bomb and namesake of a human rights prize?",
        "answer": [
          "Andrei Sakharov",
          "Sakharov",
          "Andrei Dmitrievich Sakharov"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this battle, Locris and Phocia (pr. FOH-see-uh) \"Medized\" (pr. MEED-eyzd). This\nbattle ended after Ephialtes (pr. eph-FYE-ull-TEEZ) showed the \"goat path\" to the winning\nforce, commanded by Xerxes (pr. ZERK-seez). For 10 points, name this 480 BC battle in which\nLeonidas (pr. LEE-oh-NYE-duss) led three hundred Spartans in holding a pass for three days\nagainst Persia.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Thermopylae",
          "Thermopylae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Also present at Thermopylae were troops from what city, which used the Sacred Band to\ncome to prominence in the fourth century BC and was the legendary home of Oedipus (pr. ED-uhpuss)?",
        "answer": "Thebes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man collected scrapbooks filled with pictures of Condoleeza Rice, and he once set up a tent\nnear the United Nations where he resided with his \"Amazonian Guard.\" He was killed near Sirte\n(pr. SUR-tay) in October 2011 following his overthrow in the Arab Spring. For 10 points, identify\nthis nemesis of Ronald Reagan who was the forty-year dictator of Libya.",
        "answer": [
          "Muammar Gadaffi",
          "Gadaffi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Several of Gadaffi's family members were injured by a U.S. bombing raid in 1986\nfollowing the Libyan government's assault on a disco in what city, previously the site of a 1948\n\"airlift?\"",
        "answer": [
          "West Berlin",
          "Berlin"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Bahcall and Raymond Davis searched for these particles in the Homestake experiment.\nThe 1956 experiment of Clyde Cowan and Frederick Reines confirmed their existence. Enrico\nFermi coined the name for these particles, whose \"flavor oscillation\" was a problem of late\ntwentieth-century physics. For 10 points, name these particles with very little mass and no charge.",
        "answer": [
          "neutrinos",
          "neutrino",
          "antineutrinos",
          "antineutrino",
          "solar neutrino",
          "solar neutrinos"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The neutrino was first proposed, though without a name, by what scientist, whose\nconcept of particle spin led him to formulate a namesake \"exclusion principle\" about fermions?",
        "answer": [
          "Wolfgang Pauli",
          "Pauli"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ethnicity respected administrators called yangban under a state known in Western sources\nas the \"hermit kingdom.\" This group defeated an invasion by Toyotomi Hideyoshi at Noryang.\nFrom 1910 to 1945, Japan occupied this group's land after deposing the Joseon dynasty. For 10\npoints, name this Asian ethnicity which now lives on a divided peninsula northeast of China.",
        "answer": [
          "Koreans",
          "Korean",
          "Hanguk-im",
          "Hanguk"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Korea rebuffed Hideyoshi using what large ships with covered hulls, which could blow\nsmoke out of a decorative dragon head at the prow?",
        "answer": [
          "turtle ships",
          "turtle ship",
          "gobukseon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was one of the first district attorneys in New York's Special Victims Bureau, and\nshe wrote the Democratic National Committee's rules on superdelegates. George H.W. Bush was\naccused of disrespecting her in a 1984 debate. For 10 points, name this first woman to run as a\nmajor-party Vice-Presidential candidate, appearing on the losing Walter Mondale ticket.",
        "answer": "Geraldine Ferraro"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Mondale-Ferraro ticket only won Washington, D.C. and what home state of\nMondale, which later elected Jesse Ventura governor?",
        "answer": "Minnesota"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In October 2014, a court case was filed regarding a Firestone rubber plantation in this\ncountry's town of Harbel. This country was the origin of Thomas Eric Duncan, who infected two\nnurses after arriving in Dallas with ebola. For 10 points, name this country where president Ellen\nJohnson Sirleaf governs the descendants of resettled American slaves.",
        "answer": [
          "Liberia",
          "Republic of Liberia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2014 ebola outbreak began in what northern neighbor of Liberia with capital at\nConakry, which had its first-ever democratic presidential election in 2010?",
        "answer": [
          "Guinea",
          "Republic of Guinea"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city has for decades been the center of the least populated metro area to be the home of a\nmajor American professional sports team. This city’s team is notable for its ownership structure,\nwhich consists of numerous shareholders and a stock sale in 1998 to help renovate its notoriously\ncold stadium at Lambeau (LAM-boe) Field. This city’s team name references an industry that\nwas criticized in Upton Sinclair’s The Jungle. For 10 points, name this Wisconsin city on an arm\nof Lake Michigan, with a highly successful National Football League team.",
        "answer": "Green Bay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which former Green Bay quarterback had a role in the 1998 Farrelly brothers comedy\nfilm, There’s Something About Mary?",
        "answer": [
          "Brett Favre",
          "Favre"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s wife Vibia Sabina may have had an affair with his secretary, the historian\nSuetonius. He made Marcius Turbo Praetorian Prefect and employed the frumentarii as secret\npolice. This third of the Five Good Emperors was succeeded by Antoninus Pius. For 10 points,\nname this Roman emperor who demarcated the northern limit of Roman Britain with his\nnamesake wall.",
        "answer": [
          "Hadrian",
          "Publius Aelius Hadrianus Augustus",
          "Hadrianus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hadrian’s construction of the Aelia Capitolina caused a 132 A.D. revolt directed by\nthis Simon bar Kokhba, a member of this religious group.",
        "answer": [
          "Jews",
          "Jew",
          "Jewish",
          "Judaism"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was enflamed when a court-martial acquitted Ferdinand Esterhazy. One person\ninvolved in this scandal was imprisoned on Devil’s Island until key evidence against him was\nrevealed to be forged. Emile Zola wrote the letter J’Accuse supporting that prisoner. For 10\npoints, name this scandal in which a Jewish French army captain was framed for treason.",
        "answer": [
          "Dreyfus affair",
          "Dreyfus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another 19th century French political scandal concerned Ferdinand de Lesseps’\nattempts to build what structure?",
        "answer": "Panama Canal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This color names a \"democratic movement\" which supports former Kenyan prime minister\nRaila Odinga (rah-EE-luh oh-DING-guh). A river separating both Namibia and Lesotho from\nSouth Africa is named for this color, which inspired a \"free state\" in pre-union South Africa. For\n10 points, name this color also used for the Dutch royal house and a citrus fruit.",
        "answer": "orange"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2004 Orange Revolution protested vote-rigging by Viktor Yanukovych (YAHnik-oh-vitch) in what country?",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was a failure of Brigade 2506, which landed at Playa Giron (hee-ROAN). Allen\nDulles took most of the blame for this event, which was a CIA operation with inadequate\nmilitary support. This event relied mostly on exiles and prompted its target to formally ally with\nthe Soviets. For 10 points, name this failed 1961 invasion of Cuba authorized by JFK.",
        "answer": [
          "Bay of Pigs invasion",
          "Bay of Pigs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Florida senator of Cuban descent, sometimes mentioned as a possible 2016\npresidential candidate, criticized the recent agreement to partially lift sanctions against Cuba?",
        "answer": [
          "Marco Rubio",
          "Rubio"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This product was named by Rowland Hanson, who shot down the proposed name \"Interface\nManager.\" In 1992, this product's manufacturer decided to focus on it and stop developing OS/2.\nThis product's popular versions included 3.1, NT, and 95, prior to the release of version 7 in\n2009. For 10 points, name this operating system produced by Microsoft.",
        "answer": "Windows"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "OS/2 was a joint project of Microsoft and what former titan of the industry, known as\n\"Big Blue\" for the color of both its logo and its once-mandatory employee ties?",
        "answer": "IBM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was advised by the author of Germany is Our Problem, Henry Morgenthau, as well\nas by a man who later became a conservative, Raymond Moley. This man's unofficial advisors\nwere recruited largely from Columbia University's law school and were led by Rexford Tugwell.\nThe \"brain trust\" advised, for 10 points, what man during his four terms as U.S. President?",
        "answer": [
          "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
          "F Roosevelt",
          "FDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Roosevelt was more formally advised by what Secretary of War during World War II,\nwho had previously articulated a namesake \"doctrine\" refusing to recognize Japanese conquests\nas Secretary of State?",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Stimson",
          "Stimson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire followed the proclamation of the Edict of Gulhane with a fifty year modernization\neffort called the Tanzimat Reforms. Some of its armies were composed of irregular “bashibazouks,” while others were composed of janissaries. It was known as the Sick Man of Europe\nleading up to World War I. For 10 points, name this empire which centered on Turkey.",
        "answer": [
          "Ottoman Empire",
          "Ottoman"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first president of modern Turkey was what man who implemented a namesake\npolicy of strict westernization?",
        "answer": [
          "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
          "Ataturk"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A major genre innovation during this period was the concerto grosso (con-CHAIR-toe\nGROSS-oh), which was used extensively by Arcangelo Corelli. Another composer from this\nmusical period wrote the Goldberg Variations. For 10 points, name this period in Western music\nhistory that included Johann Sebastian Bach, and came between the Renaissance and Classical\neras.",
        "answer": "Baroque"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bach composed six concertos for Christian Ludwig, who held the symbolic title of\nMargrave of what state surrounding Potsdam, Germany?",
        "answer": "Brandenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This song asks \"where is that band who so vaultingly swore\" and observes \"where the foes'\nhaughty host in dread silence reposes\" in its little-heard additional verses. The British bar song\nsong \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" was used to set the lyrics of this song. For 10 points, name this\nsong written during the British bombardment of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.",
        "answer": "The Star-Spangled Banner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort McHenry is found guarding the harbor of what major city?",
        "answer": "Baltimore"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A state park named for these people contains the Pioneer Monument and the Emigrant Trail\nMuseum. This group of people suffered an early tragedy when John Snyder was murdered. This\ngroup's poor decision to attempt the Hastings Cutoff led to them being snowed in at Truckee\nLake. For 10 points, name these people who resorted to cannibalism in the 1840s.",
        "answer": [
          "Donner Party",
          "Donner"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hastings Cutoff took the Donner Party south of what large body of water some\nmonths before they reached the Sierra Nevadas?",
        "answer": "Great Salt Lake"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Martial law was declared in this nation after the First Quarter Storm. Cardinal Jaime Sin\nhelped spearhead the overthrow of one leader of this nation. That leader’s wife had a massive\ncollection of shoes, which was left behind after the People’s Power Revolution. For 10 points,\nname this Asian nation which was formerly ruled by Ferdinand Marcos.",
        "answer": "the Philippines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Philippines was recently devastated by Yolanda, a kind of which storm?",
        "answer": "Typhoon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This procedure occurred to the writer of Forever Amber and Laura. This process required the\nauthor of Johnny Get You Gun to adopt the alias \"Robert Rich.\" For 10 points, name this process\nwhich was performed on Ring Lardner, Jr., Dalton Trumbo, and others in the Hollywood Ten,\nwho were denied work in the film industry due to their membership in the Communist Party.",
        "answer": [
          "blacklisting",
          "blacklist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trumbo was publicly acknowledged as the writer of what 1961 slave uprising drama\nstarring Kirk Douglas, ending the blacklist?",
        "answer": "Spartacus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When setting up skeletons of this species for display, museums frequently used the skull of\nCamarasaurus. That practice perpetuated Othniel Charles Marsh's belief that this species was not\nidentical to a skeleton unearthed in 1885. For 10 points, identify this dinosaur species which\nMarsh erroneously identified as separate from the fictitious \"brontosaurus.\"",
        "answer": "apatosaurus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The apatosaurus flourished during what middle period of the Mesozoic era?",
        "answer": [
          "Jurassic Period",
          "Jurassic"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man hid out at Liliesleaf Farm after the Treason Trial, where he organized the militant\ngroup Spear of the Nation. He gave the \"I Am Prepared to Die\" speech at the Rivonia Trial,\nwhich led to his lengthy imprisonment on Robben Island. For 10 points, name this man who\nultimately worked with F.W. de Klerk to end the apartheid system in South Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela",
          "Mandela",
          "Nelson Mandela"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mandela's Spear of the Nation was the paramilitary wing of what anti-apartheid group,\nwhich has been the governing political party of South Africa since 1994?",
        "answer": [
          "ANC",
          "African National Congress"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jacob Bernoulli discovered that this number is the \"force of interest,\" the limit of the interest\naccruable on a dollar by increasing the frequency of compounding. A 1727 paper on the\nexplosive force of cannons introduced this number as the base of the natural logarithm. For 10\npoints, identify this mathematical constant named for its Swiss popularizer.",
        "answer": [
          "e",
          "Euler's number",
          "Euler's constant"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Euler (pr. OY-ler) also established graph theory in an attempt to solve the problem\ninvolving seven of what kind of structure in Königsberg?",
        "answer": [
          "bridges",
          "bridge"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer incorporated \"Springfield Mountain\" and \"Camptown Races,\" along with\nexcerpts from the Gettysburg Address, into his World War II patriotic piece A Lincoln Portrait.\nHe scored ballets about Billy the Kid and about pioneers building a farmhouse in western\nPennsylvania. For 10 points, name this composer of Appalachian Spring.",
        "answer": [
          "Aaron Copland",
          "Copland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of the same biographical project that led Copland to create A Lincoln Portrait,\nVirgil Thomson set poems by what author of Leaves of Grass?",
        "answer": [
          "Walt Whitman",
          "Whitman",
          "Walter Whitman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This device was originally named for doctor Antoine Louis. The \"tricoteuse\" (pr. TRICK-awtooz) were women who knitted next to this object. This object was used on up to forty thousand\npeople at the order of Maximilien Robespierre, who found himself subject to it in 1794. For 10\npoints, name this item which was used to execute Louis XVI and others during the French\nRevolution.",
        "answer": "guillotine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The guillotine was originally used to equalize execution methods for nobles and\nmembers of what group, the peasant section of France in the Estates-General?",
        "answer": [
          "Third Estate",
          "Third"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This system was restored following the overthrow of Hippias (pr. HIP-ee-uss), after which its\ncentral feature was the boulé (pr. BOO-lay). This system involved citizens being arranged into\ndemes (pr. DEEMZ) by Cleisthenes (pr. CLICE-thuh-neez). For 10 points, identify this\npolitical system used in classical Athens, which inspired similar vote-based systems in the\nmodern world.",
        "answer": [
          "Athenian democracy",
          "democracy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Members of the boulé were selected by what method, also used to pick the tenth of an\narmy that Romans \"decimated\" and the date of the massacre of Jews in the Book of Esther?",
        "answer": [
          "by drawing of lots",
          "lot",
          "lots"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This language was used to write The Incoherence of the Philosophers, which was rebutted\nwith The Incoherence of the Incoherence. This was the language used by the medieval\nphilosopher Averroes (pr. AA-vuh-ROE-ez) and other writers based at Córdoba (pr. COREdoh-buh). For 10 points, name this language through which many Greek and Latin texts passed\nto Europe.",
        "answer": "Arabic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other Semitic language, which was the language which Jesus spoke, was\nfeatured in the Mel Gibson directed film, The Passion of the Christ?",
        "answer": "Aramaic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the twentieth century, some groups modified this holiday to use a \"cup of Miriam\" to\nsymbolize women and an orange to symbolize homosexuals. This holiday also changed in the\ntwelfth century, when its service was collected as the \"haggadah\" (pr. hah-GUH-duh). For 10\npoints, name this Jewish holiday on which the \"seder\" (pr. SAY-dur) meal includes matzah\n(MAHT-suh).",
        "answer": [
          "Passover",
          "Pesach"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What book of the Bible, in which Moses leads the Jews out of Egypt, is the focus of\nPassover?",
        "answer": [
          "Book of Exodus",
          "Exodus",
          "Sh'mot"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shortly after his death, this man was nominated for an Oscar for his work on Shall We Dance,\nfor which he wrote the song \"They Can't Take That Away From Me\" with his brother Ira. This\ncomposer used traffic horns in the score to An American in Paris and rumbas in his Cuban\nOverture. For 10 points, name this composer of the jazz concerto Rhapsody in Blue.",
        "answer": [
          "George Gershwin",
          "Gershwin"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gershwin adapted a play by DuBose Heyward into what opera, which has been both\npraised and criticized for its portrayal of black South Carolinians on Catfish Row?",
        "answer": "Porgy and Bess"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Bally and Williams corporations grew by manufacturing units for this game. Montague\nRedgrave patented the spring launcher central to this game in 1871, and in 1950, David Gottlieb\ncreated its modern form by adjusting the position of the controllable flippers. For 10 points,\nidentify this arcade game, in which points are scored for keeping the metal balls in play.",
        "answer": "pinball"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What band, which described a \"deaf, dumb, and blind\" \"Pinball Wizard\" in their rock\nopera Tommy, also recorded \"My Generation\" and \"Baba O'Reilly?\"",
        "answer": "The Who"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this African country, the Orange Democratic Movement arose following political\nfragmentation when Daniel arap Moi retired. This country's independence came shortly after\nGeneral China led the Mau Mau Rebellion against British rule here. For 10 points, name this\ncountry where the Leakey family's research on human origins took place at Olduvai Gorge.",
        "answer": "Republic of Kenya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What author of Facing Mount Kenya became Kenya's first prime minister upon\nindependence and is the father of the current Kenyan president?",
        "answer": [
          "Jomo Kenyatta",
          "Kenyatta"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party effectively ceased to function after the failure of Rufus King's Presidential\ncampaign. They were discredited when members were accused of using blue lights to signal to\nBritish ships during the War of 1812, and by their organization of the secessionist Hartford\nConvention. For 10 points, name this party of DeWitt Clinton, Alexander Hamilton, and John\nAdams.",
        "answer": [
          "Federalist Party",
          "Federalist",
          "Federalists"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What name is given to the period of political unity under James Monroe, in which\nnearly no opposition to the Democratic-Republican Party existed?",
        "answer": "Era of Good Feelings"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Popes from this family presided over the Council of Trent and the start of the Protestant\nReformation. This family of Leo X and Pius IV was targeted by the Pazzi (pr. POT-see)\nConspiracy and first rose to power in Tuscany under the banker Cosimo. For 10 points, identify\nthis political family which ruled Florence through such members as Lorenzo the Magnificent.",
        "answer": [
          "de Medici",
          "Medici"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What rival family of Spanish origin included Pope Alexander VI, the poisoner\nLucrezia, and the Machiavelli (pr. MOCK-ee-uh-VEL-ee) patron Cesare (pr. CHAY-zar-ay)?",
        "answer": "Borgias"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man discussed the fall of the First Republic in his \"Cartagena (pr. cart-uh-HAY-nuh)\nManifesto.\" This man conquered New Granada with his lieutenant, Francisco Santander, and\naccepted a Spanish surrender at Boyacá (pr. boy-uh-CAH). For 10 points, name this \"libertador\"\nwho was the icon of South American independence in Colombia and Venezuela.",
        "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bolívar had a mysterious summit at Guayaquil with what Argentine general, who\nliberated Argentina, Peru, and Chile working in tandem with Bernardo O'Higgins?",
        "answer": "Jose de San Martin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city built the luxurious Segovia Bridge over the unimpressive Manzanares (pr. mon-zuhNAH-race) River. This home of the Queen Sofia Museum became capital in 1560, replacing\nToledo. The palace El Escorial (pr. ess-core-ee-AHL) is found just outside this city, which is the\nhome of the Prado art museum. For 10 points, name this capital of Spain.",
        "answer": "Madrid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Las Ventas site in Madrid is used for what activity, the subject of Ernest\nHemingway's Death in the Afternoon?",
        "answer": [
          "bullfighting",
          "bullfight"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The informer \"Stakeknife\" infiltrated this organization, which began the \"Long War\" in the\nearly 1970s. This group claimed responsibility for killing MP Airey Neave as well as the 1984\nBrighton hotel bombing which nearly killed Margaret Thatcher. For 10 points, name this militant\nCatholic group which advocated transferring Northern Ireland away from the United Kingdom.",
        "answer": [
          "IRA",
          "Irish Republican Army",
          "Provisional IRA",
          "Provisional Irish Republican Army"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which 1972 massacre of Irish demonstrators by UK paratroopers shares its name with\na 1905 killing spree in St. Petersburg?",
        "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1850, a seeming discrepancy in this scientist’s work was resolved by Stanislao Cannizzaro.\nThis man’s breakthrough was realizing the distinction between atoms and molecules in a gas,\ncausing this veteran of the Piedmont uprising to be the namesake of the number 6.022 times 10\nto the 23rd. For 10 points, identify this discoverer of the number of particles in a mole.",
        "answer": [
          "Amadeo Avogadro",
          "Avogadro"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Avogadro was the first to correctly determine the chemical formula for what substance,\nwhich was moved against the force of gravity by Archimedes’s Screw?",
        "answer": "water"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This queen came to the throne at age six, leading to the creation of a regency council\ndominated by Axel Oxenstierna (pr. OCK-sens-TURR-nuh). In 1654, this queen shocked\nEurope by abdicating her throne and converting to Catholicism, after which she lived out her life\nin Rome. For 10 points, name this daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, an “enlightened monarch” of\nSweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Queen Christina",
          "Christina"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Christina’s energetic studies with what philosopher of Discourse on Method, whom she\nsummoned to Sweden and often woke before dawn, are thought to have caused his death?",
        "answer": "Rene Descartes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Eighth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution copied nearly verbatim this text’s prohibition\non “excessive bail and cruel and unusual punishments.” This document guaranteed freedom of\nspeech and the right to bear arms, and it also banned Catholics from succeeding to the throne.\nFor 10 points, name this 1689 law which outlined liberties prior to the Glorious Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "English Bill of Rights",
          "Bill of Rights"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What editor of The North Briton whose slogan was “No Liberty, No King” caused\nrepeated scandals in 1760s England by invoking the English Bill of Rights in his campaign\nagainst George III?",
        "answer": [
          "John Wilkes",
          "Wilkes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This god's oracle was located at Dodona. Phidias used the ivory-and-gold material\nchryselephantine to depict this god for one of the Wonders of the Ancient World. This god was\nbelieved to have survived the cannibalism of his father Cronus by being swapped with a stone.\nFor 10 points, name this thunder god and head of the Greek pantheon.",
        "answer": "Zeus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Wonder of the Ancient World was the Colossus of Rhodes, which depicted\nwhat Titan god of the sun?",
        "answer": "Helios"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was approached by Thomas Edison's agent Theo Wangemann in 1889, leading him\nto make the first-ever audio recording by a leading composer. This composer relied on Martin\nLuther's translation of the Bible as the text for his German Requiem. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer whom Hans von Bulow first grouped with Beethoven and Bach as the \"Three Bs.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Johannes Brahms",
          "Brahms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brahms was born in what city, now the second largest city by population of Germany\nand once a major center of the Hanseatic League?",
        "answer": "Hamburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician purged opponents in the \"Anti-Rightist Campaign\" after encouraging dissenters\nto identify themselves in the Hundred Flowers movement. Following news of the Secret Speech,\nthis politician led his country away from Nikita Khrushchev's Soviet Union in the late 1950s. For\n10 points, name this Long March leader and longtime \"chairman\" of Communist China.",
        "answer": [
          "Mao Zedong",
          "Mao Tse-tung"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What late 1950s program championed by Mao involved producing steel in backyard\nfurnaces in a disastrous attempt to overtake Soviet and American industrial capacity?",
        "answer": "Great Leap Forward"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This theory was advocated by John Needham due to a faulty experimental design. Lazzaro\nSpallanzani argued against this theory by showing that Needham had failed to entirely seal the\nboiled flask used before observing “animalcules.” For 10 points, name this theory finally put to\nrest by Louis Pasteur, which holds that rotting food directly creates life.",
        "answer": "spontaneous generation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What scientist, the namesake of cells found around nerves, coined the dogma that “all\ncells come from pre-existing cells” following the collapse of spontaneous generation theory?",
        "answer": [
          "Theodor Schwann",
          "Schwann"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1905, Germany's Kaiser Wilhelm II landed at this country's port of Tangier to support its\nindependence, causing a crisis with France. This country is also home to the headgear namesake\nFez and to the site of a January 1943 Allied summit that first formulated the \"unconditional\nsurrender\" doctrine. For 10 points, name this country which hosted the Casablanca Conference.",
        "answer": "Morocco"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The next Allied conference was held in what city, which was planned by Pierre\nL'Enfant and burned down after the Battle of Bladensburg in 1814?",
        "answer": [
          "Washington D.C.",
          "District of Columbia",
          "Washington"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's Awash Valley is home to the city of Hadar, where Donald Johanson found the\n\"Lucy\" skeleton. This country lost its coastline in 1991 when the UNOVER mission conducted a\nreferendum that secured independence for Eritrea. For 10 points, name this country which\nsuffered a much-publicized 1980s famine and is governed from Addis Ababa.",
        "answer": "Ethiopia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Besides Eritrea, Ethiopia is also blocked from Red Sea access by what small country,\nwhich became independent from France in 1977 after twice voting against doing so?",
        "answer": "Djibouti"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's two weeks fighting in the Confederate-affiliated Marion Rangers inspired his short\nstory \"The Private History of a Campaign That Failed.\" With Charles Dudley Warner, he wrote a\nnovel that gave its name to the post-Civil War period of prosperity in the North, The Gilded Age.\nFor 10 points, name this author who created Becky Thatcher, Huck Finn, and Tom Sawyer.",
        "answer": [
          "Mark Twain",
          "Twain",
          "Samuel Langhorne Clemens",
          "Clemens"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Twain's only success as a publisher was with a biography of what victor at Forts Henry\nand Donelson who led the successful Siege of Vicksburg?",
        "answer": [
          "Ulysses Simpson Grant",
          "Grant"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A major advance in this field was formulated by Stanley Jevons and William Marshall in the\n1880s. This field's dominant textbook in postwar America was written by Paul Samuelson, who\nsubscribed to the ideas formulated by John Maynard Keynes. For 10 points, name this social\nscience which uses supply and demand curves to study financial decision-making.",
        "answer": "economics"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Keynes's The Economic Consequences of the Peace warned that the World War I\nreparations payments imposed on what country were too harsh?",
        "answer": [
          "Germany",
          "Weimar Republic"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country underwent a religious schism known as the “Raskol” when Patriarch Nikon\nattempted to change the number of fingers used to make the sign of the cross, leading to the split\nof the Old Believers. This country is home to the world’s largest Eastern Orthodox population.\nFor 10 points, name this home country of Kirill I, the Patriarch of Moscow.",
        "answer": "Russia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Russia’s Dukhobors, another dissenting sect, largely emigrated to what country, where\nreligious diversity is explored in the popular sitcom Little Mosque on the Prairie?",
        "answer": "Canada"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1962, Henry Hammond Hess proposed that convection currents within this layer are the\ncause of seafloor spreading. In 1909, the boundary atop this layer was discovered by Andrija\nMohorovicíc (AHN-ree-huh moh-hoh-ROH-veech-itch). For 10 points, name this layer of the\nEarth which was hypothesized in the nineteenth century to lie between the core and crust.",
        "answer": "mantle"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1972, J. Tuzo Wilson proposed that mantle “hot spots” were responsible for the\nformation of what island chain, which was unified under King Kamehameha I?",
        "answer": [
          "Hawaiian islands",
          "Hawaii"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two important models of this kind of device were introduced in 1976, Chuck Peddle’s 6502\nand Zilog’s Z80. Those devices competed with the widely used 8080, from the company which\nmanufactured influential later models of these devices such as the x86, Pentium series, and i7.\nFor 10 points, name these devices at the heart of a computer, which are made by Intel.",
        "answer": [
          "microprocessors",
          "processors",
          "CPUs",
          "central processing units"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "From 1991 to 2005, what company used RISC-based PowerPC processors almost\nexclusively, such as in machines that ran its iconic System 7?",
        "answer": [
          "Apple Inc.",
          "Apple",
          "Apple Computer Inc."
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man and Benjamin Franklin are the only Americans honored as a \"Freeman of the City\"\nby St. Andrews. His victory at the American and British open and amateur tournaments gave him\nthe 1930 grand slam. This man worked with Alister MacKenzie on his most lasting creation, in\nAugusta, Georgia. For 10 points, name this founder of the Masters golf tournament.",
        "answer": [
          "Bobby Jones",
          "Jones",
          "Robert Tyre Jones Jr."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What \"Golden Bear\" holds the record of six Masters championships, two ahead of both\nArnold Palmer and Tiger Woods?",
        "answer": [
          "Jack Nicklaus",
          "Nicklaus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A picket line formed by members of this profession got into a huge brawl with police at the\nBattle of Ogreave. Members of this profession who opposed the moderate NACODS joined the\nNUM led by Arthur Scargill. Members of this profession were dubbed \"the enemy within\" by\nMargaret Thatcher. For the point, identify this profession which launched a disastrous 1984\nBritish strike which closed down facilities for extracting bitumen.",
        "answer": [
          "coal miners",
          "coal miner"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which musical about a boy who wants to be a ballet dancer features a chorus of\ndisgruntled coal miners complaining about Margaret Thatcher?",
        "answer": "Billy Elliott"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FAMOUS GREEKS",
      "prompt": "What person or god from ancient Greece...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of the Olympian gods and was depicted in a famous statue at Olympia?",
          "answer": "Zeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran naked through the streets of Syracuse shouting \"Eureka\" after discovering buoyancy?",
          "answer": "Archimedes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a cult which opposed eating beans and discovered a side length theorem for right\ntriangles?",
          "answer": "Pythagoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the \"gadfly of Athens\" whose Apology was recorded by Plato?",
          "answer": "Socrates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Offered a salt spring as a gift to Athens, which then chose Athena as its patron deity instead?",
          "answer": "Poseidon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the first book of history, The Persian Wars?",
          "answer": "Herodotus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was called the \"tenth muse\" for her accomplishments as a female poet on Lesbos?",
          "answer": "Sappho"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a \"funeral oration\" on Athenian ideals during the Peloponnesian War?",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MEDIEVAL EASTERN EUROPE",
      "prompt": "In the Middle Ages, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire which, by the 1070s, was reduced to the area around Constantinople?",
          "answer": "Byzantine, Byzantine Empire, Eastern Roman Empire, Eastern Roman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country first organized by the Piast Dynasty, which was later invaded by its neighbor\nGermany to start World War II?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim empire based in Turkey which conquered much of the region from 1308 to 1571?",
          "answer": "Ottoman, Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where the Grand Duchy of Muscovy formed around the city of Moscow?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group which briefly overran Eastern Europe after defeating the Hungarians at Mohi in 1241?",
          "answer": "Mongol, Mongols"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Vladimir the Great converted a namesake state to Christianity before it became the\nUkrainian capital?",
          "answer": "Kiev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince of Wallachia (pr. wah-LAY-kee-uh) whose practice of putting opposing soldiers on\nstakes inspired vampire legends?",
          "answer": "Vlad the Impaler, Vlad Dracula, Dracula, Vlad III, Vlad Tepes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, which shares its name with a Balkan country that declared independence in 2008 from\nSerbia?",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HERBERT HOOVER",
      "prompt": "Name the person or event from the life or presidency of Hoover that was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Name the person or event from the life or presidency of Hoover that was...\nThe four-term New Deal architect who succeeded him",
          "answer": "Franklin Delano Roosevelt, F Roosevelt, FDR"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Chicago mob kingpin convicted of tax evasion",
          "answer": "Al Capone, Capone, Alphonse Gabriel Capone"
        },
        {
          "question": "His \"Silent\" predecessor in the White House",
          "answer": "Calvin Coolidge, Coolidge, John Calvin Coolidge"
        },
        {
          "question": "The East Asian language he spoke, along with more native speakers than any other language",
          "answer": "Chinese, Mandarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The prestigious California university which he attended in its first year",
          "answer": "Stanford, Stanford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "The popular nickname for the stock market crash of October 29, 1929",
          "answer": "Black Tuesday"
        },
        {
          "question": "The disastrous 1930 tariff bill which worsened the Depression",
          "answer": "Smoot-Hawley Tariff, Smoot-Hawley, Hawley-Smoot, Hawley-Smoot Tariff"
        },
        {
          "question": "A group of World War I veterans who marched on Washington",
          "answer": "Bonus Army"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "RECONSTRUCTION",
      "prompt": "During the post-Civil War Reconstruction period in the U.S., who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State that took a long time to recover from Sherman’s March from Atlanta to Savannah?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hood-wearing group of Southern vigilantes which violently opposed black political power?",
          "answer": "KKK, Ku Klux Klan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Derogatory term given by Southerners to Northerners who moved South?",
          "answer": "carpetbaggers, carpetbagger"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was impeached during the Reconstruction Era?",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson, A Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment which prohibited slavery throughout the United States?",
          "answer": "Thirteenth Amendment, Thirteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word name given to the dominant faction in Congress which drove Reconstruction?",
          "answer": "Radical Republicans, Radical Republican"
        },
        {
          "question": "Long-unenforced Constitutional amendment barring racial discrimination in voting?",
          "answer": "Fifteenth Amendment, Fifteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "President whose inauguration ended Reconstruction as part of the Compromise of 1877?",
          "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes, Hayes, Rutherford Birchard Hayes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CHARLEMAGNE",
      "prompt": "Medieval emperor Charlemagne...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was crowned on Christmas 800 by Leo III, a holder of what top office of the Catholic\nChurch?",
          "answer": "Pope, the Papacy, Papacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Instigated the \"Carolingian\" example of what sort of period in which arts and learning revive?",
          "answer": "renaissance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched a crusade against what Germanic people, who earlier joined with the Angles to\nconquer England?",
          "answer": "Saxons, Saxon"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 797, took control of what currently second largest city in Spain?",
          "answer": "Barcelona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the son of what small-statured king?",
          "answer": "Pepin the Short, Pepin III, Pepin le Bref, Pippin der Kurze"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was gifted what kind of large animal, known as Abul-Abbas, by the Abbasid caliph?",
          "answer": "elephant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of which Germanic tribe who were earlier led by the Merovingians?",
          "answer": "Franks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the grandson of what Mayor of the Palace who won the Battle of Tours?",
          "answer": "Charles Martel, Carolus Martellus, Karl Martell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE PHILIPPINES",
      "prompt": "The present-day country of the Philippines is or was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colonized by what European power, after whose king Philip II it was named?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controlled from an 1898 war until independence by what country?",
          "answer": "United States of America, USA, America"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to the Moro people and Abu Sayyaf (pr. sai-AHF) movement, which follow what\nminority religion?",
          "answer": "Sunni Islam, Muslim, Muslims"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the Battle of Leyte (pr. LAY-tee) Gulf during which war?",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Subject to the “New Society” regime of what dictator from 1965 to 1986?",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to thousands of what item of clothing that belonged to that man's wife Imelda?",
          "answer": "shoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The destination of galleons that left the port of Acapulco from which country in the Americas?",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly led as president by what independence activist who led an anti-American insurgency\nuntil 1901?",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo, Aguinaldo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THIRTY YEARS WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Thirty Years War, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Increasingly chaotic German “empire” whose member states took opposing sides?",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "Holy Roman",
            "Hapsburg Empire",
            "Hapsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major world religion whose Protestant Reformation was one of the war’s ultimate causes?",
          "answer": "Christianity"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty which formally ended the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Peace of Westphalia",
            "Westphalia",
            "Munster",
            "Osnabruck",
            "Treaty of Westphalia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Activity which peaked during the war, and used the Malleus Mallificarum to determine whom to\nburn?",
          "answer": [
            "witch-hunts",
            "witch",
            "witch-hunting"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose pragmatic policy was made by Cardinal Richelieu (pr. ree-shell-OO)?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Event in which two diplomats were thrown out a window that sparked the fighting?",
          "answer": "Defenestration of Prague"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Sweden who was killed at the Battle of Lutzen?",
          "answer": [
            "Gustavus Adolphus",
            "Gustav II",
            "Gustav Adolf"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Watershed historical year in which it ended?",
          "answer": "1648"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE U.K. IN THE 1990’S",
      "prompt": "In the 1990s, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where the Jubilee underground line on the tube was extended?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday shortly before Easter for which a Northern Ireland peace accord was named?",
          "answer": "Good Friday"
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Party Prime Minister who began his ten-year term in 1997?",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair",
            "Anthony Charles Lynton Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose “United” soccer team was managed by Sir Alex Ferguson?",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where a Scottish parliament was established?",
          "answer": "Edinburgh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime Chancellor of the Exchequer who ultimately succeeded to the premiership in 2007?",
          "answer": [
            "Gordon Brown",
            "Brown"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Five-member \"girl group\" whose song \"Wannabe\" led the British pop culture revival?",
          "answer": "The Spice Girls"
        },
        {
          "question": "1992 treaty creating the European Union which Britain joined?",
          "answer": [
            "Maastricht Treaty",
            "Maastricht"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "JOHN QUINCY ADAMS",
      "prompt": "Fun-loving Sixth U.S. President John Quincy Adams...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the first-ever U.S. ambassador to what country, where he presented credentials at St.\nPetersburg?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Both won and lost Presidential elections against what populist Democrat known as “Old\nHickory?”",
          "answer": [
            "Andrew Jackson",
            "Jackson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Secretary of State who composed what statement against European intervention in the\nAmericas?",
          "answer": "Monroe Doctrine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kept which type of dangerous pet reptile, whose range overlaps with crocodiles only in Florida?",
          "answer": "Alligator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elevated what Great Compromiser to Secretary of State after becoming President?",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Clay",
            "Clay"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known for swimming naked in which river on which Washington DC lies?",
          "answer": "Potomac"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was forced to take on what pro-slavery extremist, who later led the nullification movement, as\nVice-President?",
          "answer": [
            "John C. Calhoun",
            "Calhoun",
            "John Caldwell Calhoun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allegedly orchestrated what underhanded plan to win the House ballot in the election of 1824?",
          "answer": "Corrupt Bargain"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "LEWIS AND CLARK",
      "prompt": "The Lewis and Clark expedition...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was intended to explore what large acquisition of land made in 1803?",
          "answer": [
            "Louisiana Purchase",
            "Louisiana territory",
            "Louisiana"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was dispatched by what President who made that acquisition?",
          "answer": [
            "Thomas Jefferson",
            "Jefferson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Departed from what city, which commemorates the event with the Gateway Arch?",
          "answer": "St. Louis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was aided by what Shosone (shuh-SHOW-nee) woman?",
          "answer": "Sacajawea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Followed what river of modern-day Washington and Oregon to the Pacific?",
          "answer": [
            "Columbia River",
            "Columbia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Formally had what name?",
          "answer": [
            "Corps of Discovery Expedition",
            "Corps of Discovery"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffered its first death near what is now Sioux City in what state?",
          "answer": "Iowa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the subject of a two-volume history by what future head of the Second Bank of the\nUnited States?",
          "answer": [
            "Nicholas Biddle",
            "Biddle"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "PEOPLE OF 1968",
      "prompt": "In 1968, who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was killed by James Earl Ray in Memphis after leading a civil rights action?",
          "answer": [
            "Martin Luther King Jr.",
            "King"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the U.S. Presidential election on his second try, defeating Hubert Humphrey?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard Nixon",
            "Nixon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Announced he would not run for reelection as president?",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon B. Johnson",
            "LBJ",
            "L Johnson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was leading the Democratic primaries prior to his assassination in Los Angeles?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert F. Kennedy",
            "RFK"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the director of the year's most controversial film, 2001: A Space Odyssey?",
          "answer": [
            "Stanley Kubrick",
            "Kubrick"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Won his tenth NBA title as the center and coach of the Boston Celtics?",
          "answer": [
            "Bill Russell",
            "Russell"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Released his Electric Ladyland Album with his \"Experience?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Jimi Hendrix",
            "Hendrix"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was accused of inciting riots in Washington, D.C. a year after resigning as leader of SNCC\n(snick)?",
          "answer": [
            "Stokely Carmichael",
            "Carmichael"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AMENDMENTS",
      "prompt": "What U.S. Constitutional amendment is or was the chief subject of...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A witness's right not to testify against himself?",
          "answer": [
            "Fifth",
            "5",
            "five",
            "5th"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Any case discussing the right to trial by jury in criminal matters?",
          "answer": [
            "Sixth",
            "6",
            "six",
            "6th"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1993 case in which Santeria worshippers asserted their religious right to sacrifice\nanimals?",
          "answer": [
            "First",
            "1",
            "one",
            "1st"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cases invoking the \"equal protection\" clause?",
          "answer": [
            "Fourteenth",
            "14",
            "fourteen",
            "14th"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mapp v. Ohio and other exclusionary rule cases?",
          "answer": [
            "Fourth",
            "4",
            "four",
            "4th"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cases arguing that the military draft constitutes involuntary servitude?",
          "answer": [
            "Thirteenth",
            "13",
            "thirteen",
            "13th"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. v Lopez which claimed \"reserved powers\" for state governments?",
          "answer": [
            "Tenth",
            "10",
            "ten",
            "10th"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2008's DC v. Heller and 2010's McDonald v. Chicago?",
          "answer": [
            "Second",
            "2",
            "two",
            "2nd"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE MAURYAN EMPIRE",
      "prompt": "The Mauryan empire...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "was on what subcontinent later home to the British Raj?",
          "answer": [
            "Indian subcontinent",
            "India"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "put edicts on rocks and what structures which can be Doric or Corinthian?",
          "answer": [
            "pillars",
            "pillar",
            "columns",
            "column"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "heard of Ashoka's conversion to what religion founded by Siddartha Gautama?",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was founded by what king who fought Seleucus Nicator?",
          "answer": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Chandragupta"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "used what refined language in which the Arthashastra was written?",
          "answer": [
            "Sanskrit language",
            "Sanskrit",
            "Samskrtam",
            "Samskrta"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "sent emissaries to what island later home to the Jaffna, Kotte, and Kandy kingdoms?",
          "answer": [
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Ceylon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "fought what type of local governors used by Persia and the Seleucids to its west?",
          "answer": [
            "satraps",
            "satrap",
            "satrapies"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "used what capital city, as did the Nanda and Gupta empires?",
          "answer": "Pataliputra"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE CONGRESS OF VIENNA",
      "prompt": "During or after the Congress of Vienna, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French emperor was exiled to Saint Helena?",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "Napoleon",
            "Napoleon I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesmen hosted the forum?",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who was victorious at Waterloo joined Castlereagh in representing the UK?",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Wellesley",
            "Wellesley",
            "the Duke of Wellington",
            "Wellington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Czar of Russia led the Russian delegation?",
          "answer": "Alexander I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country retained control of the Cape Colony and Tobago?",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Minister for Louis XVIII headed the French delegation?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand",
            "Talleyrand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country regained control of Tyrol and Ragusa?",
          "answer": "Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country was represented by Cael Lowenhielm, an illegitimate son of its king Charles XIII?",
          "answer": "Sweden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BREAKAWAY REGIONS",
      "prompt": "Who or what is or was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oil-rich African country with capital at Abuja which Biafra broke away from?",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central Asian nation which has breakaway regions in Abkhazia and South Ossetia and shares\nits name with a U.S. sate?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Catalan separatists have been protesting in Barcelona?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Middle East ethnic group who have tried to break off from Turkey and have autonomy within\nIraq",
          "answer": [
            "Kurds",
            "Kurdish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country targeted by the Western Sahara independence movement?",
          "answer": "Morocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian country which seized Goa from the Portuguese?",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-speaking West African country where Azawad tried to secede in 2012?",
          "answer": "Mali"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disputed region fought over by Armenia and Azerbaijan in a 1991 war?",
          "answer": "Nagorno-Karabakh"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE CARIBBEAN",
      "prompt": "In the history of the Caribbean islands, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Style of music originating in Trinidad practiced by Harry Belafonte (pr. beh-luh-FON-tay)\nand Lord Invader?",
          "answer": "calypso"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that colonized Martinique (pr. mar-tin-EEK), Guadeloupe (pr. gwah-duh-LOOP),\nand Haiti?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group including St. Croix (pr. CROY), St. John, and St. Thomas that has U.S. and British\nsections?",
          "answer": "Virgin Islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crop harvested under the “gang system” in the most harsh form of slavery?",
          "answer": "sugar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Regiment led by Leonard Wood and Theodore Roosevelt that captured San Juan Hill?",
          "answer": [
            "Rough Riders",
            "1st United States Volunteer Cavalry",
            "1st Cavalry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Maurice Bishop's execution led to the American Operation Urgent Fury in 1983?",
          "answer": "Grenada"
        },
        {
          "question": "British colony where the Maroon Wars involving escaped slaves took place?",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dominican dictator assassinated with American approval in 1961?",
          "answer": [
            "Rafael Trujillo",
            "Trujillo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EMANCIPATION OF SERFS",
      "prompt": "The emancipation of the world's largest serf population...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Occurred in what empire, which was ultimately ended by the deposition of Tsar Nicholas II?",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Empire",
            "Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Began in what year, also the year Abraham Lincoln's Presidency and the Civil War started?",
          "answer": "1861"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was instigated by what tsar, who was assassinated twenty years later?",
          "answer": "Alexander II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended the landlord veto over serfs engaging in what practice, the subject of the American\ncourt case Loving v. Virginia?",
          "answer": [
            "marriage",
            "weddings",
            "wedding"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was part of the fallout from Russia's defeat by Britain, France, and Turkey in what war?",
          "answer": [
            "Crimean War",
            "Crimean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led radicals to support what political position that characterized the Nechaevists, Land and\nLiberty, and The People's Will?",
          "answer": [
            "anarchism",
            "nihilism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Set up what system of elected provincial councils?",
          "answer": [
            "zemstvos",
            "zemstvo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Required that former serfs do what for forty-nine years?",
          "answer": [
            "submit redemption payments to former owners",
            "redemption payment"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EARLY PHILADELPHIA",
      "prompt": "The American city of Philadelphia was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The initial capital of what colony, set up as a religious refuge?",
          "answer": "Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "The place where what document, written by Thomas Jefferson, was signed in July 1776?",
          "answer": "Declaration of Independence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where what kite-flying inventor of bifocals published the Gazette?",
          "answer": [
            "Benjamin Franklin",
            "Franklin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the first American instance of what kind of institution, which now includes New York\nPresbyterian and Cedars-Sinai, was established?",
          "answer": "hospital"
        },
        {
          "question": "Named for the “brotherly love” exhibited by what pacifist Christian sect?",
          "answer": [
            "Quakers",
            "Quaker",
            "Religious Society of Friends",
            "Friends"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost to the British in September 1777 following Howe's defeat of Washington at what creek?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Brandywine Creek",
            "Brandywine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1793 epidemic of what disease, which Walter Reed combatted at the Panama\nCanal?",
          "answer": "yellow fever"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where what cartoon, featuring an eight-segmented snake, was published in 1754?",
          "answer": "Join or Die"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CLEOPATRA",
      "prompt": "Cleopatra VII was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The last Macedonian pharaoh of what land prior to its conquest by Rome?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The mother of a child whose father was what Ides of March assassination victim?",
          "answer": [
            "Julius Caesar",
            "Caesar",
            "Gaius Julius Caesar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Later the partner of what Second Triumvirate member who fought with Octavian?",
          "answer": [
            "Mark Antony",
            "Marcus Antonius",
            "Antony",
            "Antonius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The daughter, sister, and mother of men with what dynastic name?",
          "answer": "Ptolemy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The loser of what 31 BC naval battle which sealed her fate?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Actium",
            "Actium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Killed, in some versions, when she allowed what kind of snake to bite her?",
          "answer": "asp"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presented to her first Roman lover inside what object?",
          "answer": [
            "rolled-up carpet",
            "rug"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Able to fulfill a vow to serve a ten-million-sesterces dinner by serving what item dissolved in\nvinegar?",
          "answer": [
            "pearls",
            "pearl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WORLD WAR I",
      "prompt": "In World War I, who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The country which exited the war following the Bolshevik Revolution and organized the\nUSSR five years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Russia",
            "Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic",
            "Soviet Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The palace outside Paris where the main peace treaty was signed?",
          "answer": "Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "The archduke whose assassination sparked the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Franz Ferdinand",
            "Francis Ferdinand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The assassin responsible for that archduke's death?",
          "answer": [
            "Gavrilo Princip",
            "Princip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The country whose violated neutrality was a proximate cause of Britain’s entering the war?",
          "answer": "Belgium"
        },
        {
          "question": "The high commander of American forces in the war?",
          "answer": [
            "John Pershing",
            "John Joseph Pershing",
            "Black Jack Pershing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The German war plan which involved quickly defeating France before fighting Russia?",
          "answer": [
            "Schlieffen Plan",
            "Schlieffen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The August 1914 battle where Hindenburg and Ludendorff destroyed a Russian army?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Tannenberg",
            "Tannenberg"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MUSSOLINI",
      "prompt": "Benito Mussolini...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the dictator of what country?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Promoted what ideology named for a Roman bundle of sticks?",
          "answer": "fascism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took on what title meaning \"leader?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Il Duce",
            "Duce"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Authorized the invasion of what African country in 1935, displacing Haile Selassie (hai-LEH\nse-lah-SEE)?",
          "answer": [
            "Ethiopia",
            "Abyssinia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Entered what agreement in May 1939, formally creating the Axis?",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "Stahlpakt",
            "Patto d'Acciaio"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the invasion of what country in 1939, causing the overthrow of King Zog?",
          "answer": "Albania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed trying to flee to which country that borders Italy?",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eventually was hung upside down outside a gas station in which largest Northern Itailan city?",
          "answer": "Milan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SOUTH SEA BUBBLE",
      "prompt": "England's South Sea Bubble scandal of 1720...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Arose over a company which transported what kind of people in the \"Middle Passage\" after\nforcible abduction from Africa?",
          "answer": [
            "slaves",
            "slave"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the creation of what office, later held by Margaret Thatcher and David Cameron?",
          "answer": [
            "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom",
            "Prime Minister",
            "First Lord of the Treasury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Occurred during the reign of what first Hanoverian king?",
          "answer": "George I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to the ascension of what party, which opposed the Tories in the eighteenth-century British\nparty system?",
          "answer": [
            "Whigs",
            "Whig"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Temporarily soured the English investor class on what form of business entity which preceded\ncorporations and was prominent during the Age of Exploration?",
          "answer": "joint-stock company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arose from an attempt to exploit the Treaty of Utrecht, which ended what war in 1713?",
          "answer": [
            "War of the Spanish Succession",
            "Spanish Succession"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was resolved by what politician who dominated the British government until 1742?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Walpole",
            "Walpole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Caused the creation of what institution, which manages UK monetary policy?",
          "answer": "Bank of England"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POST-WAR ITALY",
      "prompt": "In Italy after World War II, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ideology advocated by the Red Brigades terrorist group and Italy's neighbor Yugoslavia?",
          "answer": [
            "Communism",
            "Marxism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organized crime phenomenon which was curtailed in the \"Maxi trial?\"",
          "answer": "the mafia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization formed by the Maastricht Treaty which Italy was an architect of?",
          "answer": [
            "European Union",
            "EU"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Western military alliance which orchestrated Operation Gladio in Italy?",
          "answer": [
            "NATO",
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Media mogul who became Italy's right-wing prime minister three times and was frequently\ncharged with corruption?",
          "answer": [
            "Silvio Berlusconi",
            "Berlusconi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Milan-based designer who founded what is now Italy's largest men's fashion house in 1975?",
          "answer": [
            "Giorgio Armani",
            "Armani"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Umbrella auto manufacturer which now owns Ferrari, Maserati, and Chrysler?",
          "answer": "Fiat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name commonly given to the period of political violence from 1969 to the mid-1980s?",
          "answer": [
            "Years of Lead",
            "Anni di piombo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MILLARD FILLMORE",
      "prompt": "U.S. President Millard Fillmore...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the last President to belong to neither of what two parties?",
          "answer": [
            "Democrats and Republicans",
            "Democrat and Republican"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded what “Old Rough and Ready” Mexican War hero, who died in office?",
          "answer": [
            "Zachary Taylor",
            "Taylor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first President inaugurated after the dedication of what 555-foot obelisk in D.C.?",
          "answer": "Washington Monument"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent what \"Commodore\" to open trade with Japan?",
          "answer": [
            "Matthew Perry",
            "M Perry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Recognized Utah as a territory under the leadership of what Mormon church president?",
          "answer": [
            "Brigham Young",
            "Young"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed what omnibus bill which sought to resolve free-slave state concerns?",
          "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted to regain the Presidency in 1856 under the banner of what third party?",
          "answer": [
            "Know-Nothing Party",
            "Know-Nothing",
            "American Party",
            "American"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Approved the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty, which concerned the future construction of what route?",
          "answer": "Panama Canal"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "OTTOMAN GROUPS",
      "prompt": "What group within the Ottoman Empire was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The ethnicity of the ruling class?",
          "answer": [
            "Turks",
            "Turk",
            "Turkish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allowed to maintain the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem and placed under the\n\"protection\" of the Russian tsar?",
          "answer": [
            "Christians",
            "Christian"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite soldiers who were massacred in the Auspicious Incident?",
          "answer": "Janissaries"
        },
        {
          "question": "The section of the sultan's palace where his wives and concubines lived, or, by extension, that\ngroup of women themselves?",
          "answer": "harem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led in a namesake \"revolt\" by Faisal (FAI-sul) and T.E. Lawrence?",
          "answer": [
            "Arabs",
            "Arab"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Increased in number following their expulsion from Spain, and able to compose the Shulchan\nAruch (SHOOL-kahn aa-ROOK) legal code in Damascus?",
          "answer": [
            "Jews",
            "Jew"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The profession of forty percent of the empire's subjects, who had to pay taxes in kind?",
          "answer": [
            "farmers",
            "farmer",
            "agriculture"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The ethnicity which went to war against the Ottomans for a final time under Abbas I?",
          "answer": [
            "Persians",
            "Persian",
            "Iranians",
            "Iranian"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AMERICAN REVOLUTIONARY WAR LEADERS",
      "prompt": "What military man during the American Revolution was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Continental Army who became the first U.S. President?",
          "answer": [
            "George Washington",
            "Washington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Saratoga victor who defected to the British as part of a plot to surrender West Point?",
          "answer": [
            "Benedict Arnold",
            "Arnold"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Artillery officer who later served as the First US Secretary of War?",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Knox",
            "Knox"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who cut off the British retreat at Yorktown?",
          "answer": [
            "Marquis de Lafayette",
            "Lafayette",
            "Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier de La Fayette",
            "La Fayette"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Swamp Fox” who launched guerilla attacks in South Carolina?",
          "answer": [
            "Francis Marion",
            "Marion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Polish “father of American cavalry” who died at Savannah?",
          "answer": [
            "Casimir Pulaski",
            "Pulaski",
            "Kazimierz Michal Wladyslaw Wiktor Pulaski"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Prussian who served as chief of staff and wrote the U.S. Army drill manual?",
          "answer": [
            "Baron von Steuben",
            "Steuben",
            "Friedrich Wilhelm August Heinrich Ferdinand von Steuben"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander who became notorious as “Bloody Ban” after killing POWs at the\nWaxhaw Massacre?",
          "answer": [
            "Banastre Tarleton",
            "Tarleton"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE COURT OF THE FRENCH KING",
      "prompt": "What important person in the reigns of the final four kings of pre-Revolutionary France was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A radical free speech advocate and the author of Candide?",
          "answer": [
            "Voltaire",
            "Francois-Marie Arouet",
            "Arouet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "A finance minister whose cheapness caused his name to be applied to an all-black outline\nportrait?",
          "answer": [
            "Etienne de Silhouette",
            "Silhouette"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The king from 1610 to 1643 who ended the regency of Marie de Medici?",
          "answer": "Louis XIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "The thinker who explained separation of powers in The Spirit of the Laws?",
          "answer": [
            "Baron Montesquieu",
            "Charles-Louis de Secondat",
            "Secondat"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Catholic \"Red Eminence\" who dominated the court in the 1620s and 30s?",
          "answer": [
            "Cardinal Richelieu",
            "Richelieu",
            "Armand Jean du Plessis",
            "du Plessis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The influential mistress of Louis XV with a flamboyant hairstyle?",
          "answer": [
            "Madame de Pompadour",
            "Pompadour"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The formulator of the law of conservation of mass and the metric system who was executed by\nthe Revolution despite being the \"Father of Modern Chemistry?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Antoine Lavoisier",
            "Lavoisier"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The composer of religious music for Louis XIV who died after shattering his foot with a\nbaton?",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Baptiste Lully",
            "Lully"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The use of this three word phrase ended a secret program by which Ryan Crocker coordinated the capture of Al-Qaeda operatives. This phrase originally ended with the word \"hatred\" when David Frum wrote it into a section of the (20 pts) ",
        "2002 State of the Union Address that argued for the overthrow of Saddam Hussein. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, give this threeword phrase used by George W. Bush to describe Iraq, Iran, and North Korea by analogy to an earlier grouping of Germany, Italy, and Japan."
      ],
      "answer": "axis of evil"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A major book about these places was based heavily on the recollections of Georg Tenno. These places were initially described only in \"samizdat\" literature, whose (20 pts) ",
        "possession could get a person sent to these places, which were the subject of the (10 pts) ",
        "Kolyma Tales. For 10 points, name these places whose \"archipelago\" is the subject of a book by Alexander Solzhenitsyn, who also set One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich in one of these forced Soviet labor camps."
      ],
      "answer": "gulag, gulags"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this era, Josquin des Prez (pr. JOHS-kin day PRAY) made advances in polyphony (puh-LIFF-uh-nee), and Giovanni da Palestrina wrote the (20 pts) ",
        "Pope Marcellus Mass. This era's music came under fire at the Council of Trent and was succeeded by the (10 pts) ",
        "Baroque period. For 10 points, identify this period in Western musical history in which motets and masses were the dominant form of music, and which shares its name with a \"rebirth\" in literature and visual arts."
      ],
      "answer": "the Renaissance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This substance was the subject of the \"Letter to Queen Victoria\" sent by Commissioner Lin, who burned chests full of it on the beach. This substance was mixed with alcohol to make the eighteenth-century medicine (20 pts) ",
        "\"laudanum\" and was consumed in namesake \"dens.\" The seizure of the Arrow sparked a second (10 pts) ",
        "war named for this substance. For 10 points, identify this narcotic whose first war ended when the Treaty of Nanking granted European concessions in China."
      ],
      "answer": "opium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Herbert Fairbank first explained the potential for this system in 1939 after expanding the Pershing Map. This system was authorized by a 1956 law but not completed until 1992, at a cost of 114 (20 pts) ",
        "billion dollars. This system was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who had seen the uses of the (10 pts) ",
        "Autobahn system while serving in Germany. For 10 points, identify this road network which includes even-numbered east-west routes and odd-numbered north-south routes."
      ],
      "answer": "Interstate, Interstate Highway System, interstate highways"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Russell S. Penniman found a cheaper way to make this product, which must be periodically rotated to avoid the pooling of its active component out of the (20 pts) ",
        "sawdust medium. This product reduced the danger of using black powder or unmodified (10 pts) ",
        "nitroglycerin, and led to its inventor being dubbed \"the merchant of death.\" For 10 points, identify this explosive with mining and military applications, which requires a blasting cap and was devised by Alfred Nobel."
      ],
      "answer": "dynamite"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Ascham described the use of this weapon in the manual Toxophilus, and it survived in the British army until World War II, when Jack Churchill killed a Nazi soldier with one of them. These weapons were sometimes named for the (20 pts) ",
        "Welsh people who invented them and perfected their use, and they were used to great effect by the English at (10 pts) ",
        "Agincourt (pr. AA-jin-core). For 10 points, name this six-foot-tall archery weapon which replaced the crossbow."
      ],
      "answer": "longbow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was aided by a 1946 enforcement of the Smoke Control Ordinance under David Lawrence. Factory workers in this city told of Joe Magerac and invented a method of cooking steak that produces a charred exterior and raw inside. This city was where (20 pts) ",
        "Pinkerton detectives were hired to break the Homestead strike by Henry Clay Frick and Andrew (10 pts) ",
        "Carnegie. For 10 points, name this former center of steel production, which is at the head of the Ohio River in Western Pennsylvania."
      ],
      "answer": "Pittsburgh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Because two million acres in this American state were set aside for veterans, the land became known as the \"Military Tract\" and towns there were named Pompey, Solon, and Scipio. This state's \"burned-over district\" was the center of the (20 pts) ",
        "Second Great Awakening, and its city of (10 pts) ",
        "Cooperstown became the home of the Baseball Hall of Fame due to an erroneous belief that the game was invented there. For 10 points, name this home of the Finger Lakes and Buffalo."
      ],
      "answer": "New York"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Buffalo Springfield insisted that the song \"For What It's Worth\" was about the Sunset Strip curfew riots and not this event. This event was the subject of Country Joe and the Fish's biggest hit. A veteran of this conflict is the subject of (20 pts) ",
        "Bruce Springsteen's \"Born in the USA,\" and a (10 pts) ",
        "protest against this conflict inspired Neil Young to write \"Ohio\" about the Kent State shootings. For 10 points, name this war which inspired copious protest music in the late 1960s."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War, Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1844, the U.S. dispatched missionary Peter Parker and attorney Caleb Cushing to this country to negotiate a trade pact. This country signed the 1868 Burlingame Treaty with the United States. This country's natives were the subject of the (20 pts) ",
        "Geary Act, and were prohibited from entering the U.S. between 1882 and 1943 under a namesake (10 pts) ",
        "\"Exclusion Act.\" For 10 points, name this country which is now, after Canada, the second-largest trade partner of the U.S."
      ],
      "answer": "China, People's Republic of China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An important 1878 piece for this instrument was composed for the virtuoso Joseph Joachim (pr. YO-zef YO-ah-keem). This instrument was played by a composer of (20 pts) ",
        "twenty-four caprices who allegedly made a deal with the devil, Niccolò (10 pts) ",
        "Paganini. Many valuable examples of this instrument were created by the master craftsman Antonio Stradivari. For 10 points, name this string instrument which an orchestra's concertmaster plays."
      ],
      "answer": "violin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization was formed at the suggestion of Mary White Ovington following the Springfield riot of 1908, and it absorbed many veterans of the Niagara Movement. This organization awards the (20 pts) ",
        "Spingarn Medals, and its first major effort was publishing The Crisis under the editorship of (10 pts) ",
        "W.E.B. DuBois (pr. doo-BOYZ). For 10 points, name this organization which led the anti-segregationist movement for much of the twentieth century."
      ],
      "answer": "NAACP, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won a Nobel Prize in Literature for his History of the English-Speaking Peoples. This man was First Lord of the Admiralty during the (20 pts) ",
        "Gallipoli disaster, though his \"wilderness years\" eventually ended and allowed him to make the \"we shall (10 pts) ",
        "fight them on the beaches\" speech. He was defeated in his first re-election bid by Clement Attlee. For 10 points, name this leader of the national unity government of the U.K. during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill, Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this organization were represented in the Reichstag by the Centre Party. This organization was targeted by Adalbert von Falk's May Laws, part of the (20 pts) ",
        "Kulturkampf (pr. KOOL-tur-kompf) against it launched by Otto von Bismarck. A leader of this organization who was accused of turning a blind eye to the Holocaust was (10 pts) ",
        "Pius XII. For 10 points, name this organization which is the predominant Christian denomination in southern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church, Catholic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) People who opposed this action wrote under the pen names Cato, Brutus, and the Federal Farmer, and were most likely George Clinton, Robert Yates, and Mercy Otis Warren. This action was supported in a series of (20 pts) ",
        "letters to the New York Packet written by \"Publius,\" a collective pseudonym for James (10 pts) ",
        "Madison, John Jay, and Alexander Hamilton. For 10 points, what was this action which was advocated in the Federalist Papers and created the present U.S. government?"
      ],
      "answer": "ratifying the U.S. Constitution, ratifying Constitution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first-ever U.S. Cabinet member to serve a prison sentence did so as a result of this scandal. This scandal's investigation by Thomas Walsh led to the Supreme Court case of McGrain v. Daugherty, which held that Congress may require people to testify. It involved (20 pts) ",
        "land in the Black Hills which Albert Fall, the Secretary of the Interior, leased to (10 pts) ",
        "oil prospectors at cut rates. For 10 points, identify this defining scandal of the Warren Harding administration."
      ],
      "answer": "Teapot Dome"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city was the site of a Church council held five years before the Council of Constance which elected Alexander V as Pope in an attempt to end the Western Schism. This city was the loser of the Battle of (20 pts) ",
        "Meloria, and it was where a man allegedly dropped (10 pts) ",
        "cannonballs out of a window in order to measure acceleration. For 10 points, name this home to a gravitational experiment by Galileo, who made use of an architectural blunder that created its \"leaning tower.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A person by this name was the fanatically Catholic Duke of Guise (pr. GHEEZ) while\nanother man of this name was the final king of the Valois (pr. val-WAH) Dynasty. Another\nman of this name was originally the king of (20 pts) ",
        "Navarre and said \"Paris is worth a mass\" to\nexplain his conversion to Catholicism. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, give this name of three men who fought\nthe last French War of Religion, including the first Bourbon king of France."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry",
        "Henri"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man died mysteriously at the Grinder's Stand inn in 1809 while journeying on the\nNatchez Trace. In 1804, he departed from St. Louis (20 pts) ",
        "with another man whom he had hired\nfor the Corps of Discovery. Along the way, he met (10 pts) ",
        "Sacajawea and reached the British\nOregon Territory. For 10 points, name this man who was appointed to explore western North\nAmerica by Thomas Jefferson along with William Clark."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Meriwether Lewis",
        "Lewis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) When this phenomenon is enacted to target negative externalities, it is known as\n\"Pigouvian\" (pr. pig-OO-vee-uhn). According to supply-side economics, this process produces\nsimilar (20 pts) ",
        "revenues at the extremes, as demonstrated by the Laffer curve. A slogan in the\nAmerican revolution decried the imposition of this process (10 pts) ",
        "\"without representation.\" For 10\npoints, identify this process in which the government legally compels people to provide money."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "taxation",
        "tax"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During primaries in this Presidential election year, hippies were urged to shave in the\n\"keep clean for Gene\" campaign. A ticket in this election year contained a man who\npromised to \"bomb them back into the (20 pts) ",
        "Stone Age\" and was the last third-party\nPresidential ticket to capture multiple electoral votes. The success of George (10 pts) ",
        "Wallace in\nthis election year inspired the alleged \"Southern Strategy.\" For 10 points, name this year in which\nHubert Humphrey lost to Richard Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "68",
        "1968"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man led a legion in support of the Colorado Party during the Uruguayan Civil War.\nHe later took command of the Hunters of the Alps to fight against Austria, which challenged\nhis project that included the Siege of (20 pts) ",
        "Gaeta undertaken by the Expedition of the\nThousand. This man allied with Count (10 pts) ",
        "Cavour to achieve the Risorgimento (pr. reeSORGE-ee-MEN-toe). For 10 points, name this general who led the Redshirts on a successful\ncampaign to unify Italy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Giuseppe Garibaldi",
        "Garibaldi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Investigator Leonora Barry advocated for women within this organization. This\norganization was led by a \"Grand Master Workman\" and was an expansion of a\nPhiladelphia-based tailors' union led by (20 pts) ",
        "Uriah Stephens. The Union Pacific strike of 1884\nwas its high-water mark, and it eventually lost influence due to excluding (10 pts) ",
        "unskilled\nworkers and most blacks. For 10 points, name this first large trade union in the U.S., which grew\nunder Terrence Powderley."
      ],
      "answer": "Knights of Labor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The latest date for this facility's destruction is 642, according to the story blaming Amr ibn\nal As, though it is also believed that Theophilus ordered it (20 pts) ",
        "burned in 391 or that it fell\nvictim to the chaos of the Zenobia revolt. This building housed thousands of (10 pts) ",
        "scrolls and\ntablets and was the jewel of a complex dedicated to the Muses by Ptolemy (pr. TAH-luh-mee).\nFor 10 points, name this center of learning in the Classical world, which was found in Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Library of Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a musical named for this dance, Judge Forestier (pr. for-ess-TEER) finally concludes\nthat \"It's All Right With Me.\" That Cole Porter musical discusses the scandal that this\ndance, which is in 2/4 time and based on the quadrille (pr. kwah-DREEL), caused when it was\nintroduced to (20 pts) ",
        "Paris in 1858. This dance first appeared in Jacques (10 pts) ",
        "Offenbach's Orpheus\nin the Underworld. For 10 points, name this characteristic French music hall dance involving\nwomen kicking their legs high."
      ],
      "answer": "the can-can"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man revised the pamphlet The Falsifiers of History to present his side of 1930s events,\nand he gave the \"Dizzy From Success\" speech to explain why he was modifying goals of the (20 pts) ",
        "First Five-Year Plan. This leader orchestrated the \"show trials\" of army generals and\nothers, decimating his military before the (10 pts) ",
        "Nazi invasion of his country in Operation\nBarbarossa. For 10 points, name this fan of gulags who was the dictator of the Soviet Union from\n1924 to 1953."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Joseph Stalin",
        "Ioseb Besarionis Dze Jugashvili",
        "Jugashvili"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man published regular weather data in his Meteorological Observations. As he was\nless influential in his own time than Jakob Berzelius, it was Berzelius's endorsement which\nled to acceptance of his ideas. He was the first to state what is now called (20 pts) ",
        "Charles's Law\nand form a theory about red-green colorblindness, as well as the law of (10 pts) ",
        "partial pressures.\nFor 10 points, name this early nineteenth century British scientist who popularized the modern\nidea of atoms."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Dalton",
        "Dalton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The founder of this religion is depicted reacting to sweetness in the painting The Vinegar\nTasters. Mystics within this religion formed the Five Pecks of Rice Society, which formed a\nbreakaway state that followed the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Celestial Master.\" This religion was believed to be\nfounded by a 900-year-old man who was forced to write down The Book of the (10 pts) ",
        "Way\nbefore leaving for the West. For 10 points, name this traditional, non-Confucian religion of\nChina."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Daoism",
        "Taoism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A news photographer captured an assault on Richard Frankensteen, a leader of this\nunion, by surrendering fake photo plates. This union, now led by Dennis Williams,\nrepresents many (20 pts) ",
        "graduate students. This union, which operated a dedicated radio\nstation, was involved in the \"Battle of the (10 pts) ",
        "Overpass\" during its leadership by Walter\nReuther. The 1937 Flint sit-down strike gave it official recognition. For 10 points, name this\nunion of car industry employees."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "UAW",
        "United Automobile Workers",
        "United Auto Workers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Mehmet Ali Ağca attempted to assassinate someone holding this position. Eugenio Pacelli\nwas criticized for his silence over the Holocaust while he held it. One of these people\ncondemned (20 pts) ",
        "contraception in Humanae Vitae. Karol Wojtyla was the first non- (10 pts) ",
        "Italian\nto hold this position in over 400 years, and Jorge Bergoglio became the first non-European in\nover 1,000 years when he succeeded Benedict XVI. For 10 points, name this head of the Roman\nCatholic Church."
      ],
      "answer": "Pope"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This westward-facing building is the largest in a similarly-named city that also houses\nthe Bayon, the Ta Prohm, and artificial lakes called baray. Its cross-shaped Grand Terrace\nstands in front of five towers laid out like the dots on a die. (20 pts) ",
        "Suryavarman II began\nconstruction on this site, which was first dedicated to (10 pts) ",
        "Vishnu before it became Buddhist.\nFor 10 points, name this tallest temple built by the Khmer empire, which appears in white on the\nnational flag of Cambodia."
      ],
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These things were first discovered using Charles Chamberlain's porcelain filters. By\n1910, Peyton Rous demonstrated their role in cancers. In 1892, Dmitri Ivanovsky\ndemonstrated that these things caused the (20 pts) ",
        "tobacco mosaic disease. Walter Reed found\nthe first large-scale human consequence of these things, when he showed that one of them\ncauses (*) yellow fever. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this quasi-living genetic information vector that is\nnot a bacteria."
      ],
      "answer": "virus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At one of these events, a man denounced an idea as \"thin as a homeopathic soup made\nby boiling the shadow of a pigeon that starved to death.\" These events, which were held in\ntowns such as (20 pts) ",
        "Alton, Galesburg, and Quincy, failed to prevent the (10 pts) ",
        "\"Little Giant\" from\nwinning a Senatorial election. For 10 points, what were these 1858 clashes of rhetoric in Illinois,\nwhich set up a rematch among their participants in the Presidential election of two years later?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lincoln-Douglas debates",
        "Lincoln-Douglas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person was the subject of a \"nullification trial\" convened by Calixtus III. This\nperson led troops that captured John Talbot at the Battle of Patay. After getting an\naudience with (20 pts) ",
        "Charles VII, this person correctly identified the disguised king. This hero\nof the Siege of (10 pts) ",
        "Orleans claimed to have visions of St. Michael and St. Margaret. For 10\npoints, name this woman who was burned at the stake after fighting for the French in the\nHundred Year's War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jon of Arc",
        "Joan Arc",
        "Jeanne d'Arc",
        "Jeanne Arc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) One leader of this nation has attempted to re-nationalize its YPF oil company, while\nanother formed the Triple-A death squad to counteract leftist elements. The Justicialist\nparty in this nation split into three parts, one of which was led by former president Carlos (20 pts) ",
        "Menem. Another leader of this nation was overthrown by Jorge Videla’s junta, which\nthen instigated the (10 pts) ",
        "Dirty War. For 10 points, name this nation once headed by Juan Peron."
      ],
      "answer": "Argentina"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In mid-2014, popular examples of this kind of product included the Moto 360 and Pebble\nSteel. Samsung launched several of these products under the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Gear\" line, and these\nproducts are named for a Sony line that integrates with (10 pts) ",
        "Android operating systems. For\n10 points, Apple caused a stir by announcing the launch of their version of what kind of wearable\ntechnology product, which is often used for fitness monitoring or portable media capabilities?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "smart watches",
        "smart watch"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s father was an Olympic boxer for Iran, while he himself won the 1996\nOlympic gold medal in men’s singles for tennis. In the early 1990’s, he attracted\ncontroversy for his flamboyant (20 pts) ",
        "dress, but also gained an endorsement deal for Canon\ncameras where he said the tagline, “Image is everything.” He is the most recent American\nto achieve the career (10 pts) ",
        "Grand Slam, and he is married to German legend Steffi Graf. For 10\npoints, name this tennis player and Las Vegas native, who was perhaps the greatest rival to Pete\nSampras."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Andre",
        "Agassi",
        "Agassi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Norse mythology, it was believed that the world-ending Ragnarok would include the\nwolf Skoll finally succeeding in his quest to eat this object. The national god of the Incas,\nInti, was the god of this thing. Japanese (20 pts) ",
        "emperors once titled themselves as descendants\nof a goddess of this thing, (10 pts) ",
        "Amaterasu. Similarly, Egyptians placed great importance on the\nmain god of this thing, Ra. For 10 points, name this astronomical body often worshipped by\npolytheists."
      ],
      "answer": "the sun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was embarrassed by the 2002 release of Nixon White House tapes in which he\naccused Jews of belonging to the \"synagogue of Satan.\" This man, who has taken credit for\nconvincing Dwight Eisenhower to (20 pts) ",
        "desegregate schools in Arkansas, became famous for\nhis Festival of Hope and (10 pts) ",
        "ecumenical revivals, which close with the hymn \"Just As I Am.\"\nFor 10 points, name this frequent Presidential advisor and most successful evangelist in\nAmerican history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Billy Graham",
        "Graham"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this film, the title character builds a Chicago opera house in an attempt to make his\nsecond wife, Susan Alexander, into a movie star. Jerry Thompson attempts to research the\nlife of this film’s title character, who had built the (20 pts) ",
        "Xanadu estate. This movie begins\nwith its title character dropping a snowglobe after whispering the word (10 pts) ",
        "“Rosebud.” For\n10 points, name this Orson Welles movie about a newspaper magnate."
      ],
      "answer": "Citizen Kane"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man replaced Vin Diesel in the lead role for the sequel XxX: State of the Union. This\nman was attacked by his former bandmates on the EP 100 Miles and Runnin at the same\ntime that he released his solo debut, (20 pts) ",
        "AmeriKKKa's Most Wanted. This star of the (10 pts) ",
        "Barbershop series wrote more lyrics for NWA than any other member. For 10 points, name this\ngangsta rapper turned family comedian, the star of the Are We There Yet? movies."
      ],
      "answer": "Ice Cube"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man commissioned a battle flag with a motto sewn on it that he attributed to James\nLawrence, \"Don't Give Up the Ship.\" This man opposed Jesse Elliot, the captain of the\nNiagara, at (20 pts) ",
        "Put-In Bay. He issued the message \"We have (10 pts) ",
        "met the enemy and they are\nours\" to his commander in the field, William Henry Harrison. For 10 points, name this naval\ncommander who defeated the British at the Battle of Lake Erie during the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Hazard Perry",
        "Perry"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's central bank adopted a policy of “forward guidance” for future interest\nrates after the 2008 financial crisis. It froze Icelandic bank assets in 2008 after Iceland\nrefused to guarantee its banks' debts to creditors in this country. The Chancellor of the (20 pts) ",
        "Exchequer proposed large spending cuts in 2010 as part of the austerity program of its\ncurrent prime minister, (10 pts) ",
        "David Cameron. For 10 points, name this country whose\ngovernment nationalized the Royal Bank of Scotland."
      ],
      "answer": "United Kingdom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Charles Ogle mockingly accused Martin van Buren of eating with a spoon made of these\nsubstance. A speech about this substance exclaimed \"you shall not press down upon the\nbrow of labor this (20 pts) ",
        "crown of thorns.\" This substance was sought by men who went to the (10 pts) ",
        "Klondike, the 49ers, and other prospectors. For 10 points, name this substance whose\n\"standard\" was, until 1971, the basis of American money."
      ],
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Letters leaked by Henry Simpson McComb first exposed this company's actions to the\nNew York Sun. This company was organized by George Train and Thomas (20 pts) ",
        "Durant, and\nit began a cozy relationship with Congress following the installation of Oakes (10 pts) ",
        "Ames as\nits president. It held an inflated contract with the Union Pacific railroad. For 10 points, name this\ncompany at the center of an 1872 Grant administration scandal involving political graft."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Credit Mobilier of America",
        "Credit Mobilier"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A succession war named for this area began on the death of Maximilian Joseph in 1777\nand was also known as the \"potato war.\" Motifs from Wagner (pr. VOG-ner) operas are\nused to decorate the (20 pts) ",
        "Neuschwanstein (pr. noy-SHVON-shtine) Castle in this region,\nwhich was built by its (10 pts) ",
        "\"Mad\" king Ludwig II. For 10 points, name this southeastern German\nstate and historic kingdom, where many German Catholics and the city of Munich can be found."
      ],
      "answer": "Bavaria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The protagonist of this TV show insisted that if Ronald Reagan dyed his hair, he only did\nso \"to show his strength to the Communists,\" and had his faith in the Republican Party\ntested when he discovered that (20 pts) ",
        "George W. Bush had a limp handshake. An episode of\nthis show is about a plot to steal Santa Anna's (10 pts) ",
        "wooden leg on its way back to Mexico, and\nin another, former governor Ann Richards dates Bill. For 10 points, name this former FOX\ncartoon about Arlen, Texas."
      ],
      "answer": "King of the Hill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These places grew up after World War II on the \"Levittown\" model. These places were\nthe destination of \"white flight,\" and attempts to combine their (20 pts) ",
        "school systems with\nmajority-black districts in the 1970s led to \"busing\" programs. The automotive\ndependence of these places is criticized for contributing to (10 pts) ",
        "\"sprawl.\" For 10 points, name\nthese places to which middle-class Americans shifted after the 1950s, from which many people\ncommute to cities."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "suburbs",
        "suburb"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement's victory was secured at the Battle of Vertières (pr. VAIR-tee-air). This\nmovement was started by the \"houngan\" Dutty Boukman, and it was partially betrayed to\nCharles (20 pts) ",
        "Leclerc. Following this movement's success, its victors immediately split into\nfactions supporting either Henri (10 pts) ",
        "Christophe or Jean-Jacques Dessalines. For 10 points,\nname this successful slave rebellion which was initially led by Toussaint L'Ouverture (pr. TOOsahn ver-TOR)."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Haitian revolution",
        "slave revolt in Haiti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These items may have been named for the shipworkers on Hog Island who enjoyed them\nin the Philadelphia area. Another name for these items is attributed to Dominic Conti, who\ntook inspiration from viewing the (20 pts) ",
        "Fenian Ram on display in a museum. Less certain\norigins for this object’s names include the New England term (10 pts) ",
        "“grinder” and the New\nYork area “hero.” For 10 points, name this lunch food popularized by Italian-Americans and now\nserved as a “five-dollar footlong.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "subs",
        "sub",
        "hoagies",
        "hoagie"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man coined the name \"scissors crisis\" during the period of the New Economic\nPolicy. He also created the term \"degenerated workers state\" to summarize his views on\nwhat the (20 pts) ",
        "Soviet Union became following his deposition as head of the Red Army. He\nwas ultimately killed in (10 pts) ",
        "Mexico by Ramon Mercador. For 10 points, name this member of\nthe Left Opposition who was outmaneuvered by Joseph Stalin for leadership of the USSR."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Leon Trotsky",
        "Trotsky"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Frank Morris and the Anglin brothers left fake heads behind at this location in 1962.\nFrom 1969 to 1971, this location was occupied in a political protest by the Indians of All\nTribes. Burt (20 pts) ",
        "Lancaster played the title role in a film about Robert Stroud, the\n\"birdman\" of this place. Officially, no one ever (10 pts) ",
        "escaped from this place, assuming Morris\nand Anglin drowned before reaching Angel Island. For 10 points, name this former prison and\nisland off San Francisco."
      ],
      "answer": "Alcatraz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This king was the beneficiary of the original Act of Supremacy. He raised funds for the\nmiddle part of his reign by dissolving nearly all monasteries in his kingdom, with the\nassistance of his first administrator Thomas (20 pts) ",
        "Wolsey. This king was the father of\nEdward VI, (10 pts) ",
        "Mary I, and Elizabeth I. For 10 points, name this king whose attempt to divorce\nCatherine of Aragon triggered the English Reformation and his five subsequent marriages."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry VIII"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During primaries for this year's election, a candidate won applause in a high school\ngymnasium after yelling \"I am paying for this microphone!\" Another party's primaries in\nthis election year featured a strong challenge to the incumbent from (20 pts) ",
        "Ted Kennedy. This\nelection also included independent candidate John Anderson. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, identify this\nelection year which resulted in the end of Jimmy Carter's Presidency and the start of the Ronald\nReagan administration."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States Presidential election of 1980",
        "1980"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This Supreme Court case was analogous to the Sweatt v. Painter decision which came\ndown four years earlier. The ruling in this Supreme Court case drew on Kenneth and\nMamie Clark's (20 pts) ",
        "doll experiments. A followup to this case ordered its ruling implemented\n\"with all deliberate speed.\" Thurgood (10 pts) ",
        "Marshall successfully argued this case on behalf of\nthe NAACP. For 10 points, name this unanimous 1954 ruling of the Warren court against\nsegregated public schools."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka",
        "Kansas",
        "Brown"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Kicking Bear adapted a Mormon belief into an auxiliary practice of this movement, in\nwhich bullet-repelling shirts were worn. This movement's main ritual was adapted from\nearlier \"circle\" performances by (20 pts) ",
        "Wodziwob, and it spread across the Plains under the\nleadership of (10 pts) ",
        "Wovoka, who preached that it would end white encroachment on Indian lands.\nFor 10 points, name this Indian religious movement whose practitioners were massacred in 1890\nat Wounded Knee."
      ],
      "answer": "Ghost Dance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To show that the Federal Reserve's contractionary economic policy exacerbated the\nGreat Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on A (20 pts) ",
        "y exacerbated the\nGreat Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on A (+) Monetary History of\nthe United States. He popularized his ideas on the relationship between the free market and\nindividual liberty in the PBS miniseries Free to Choose. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this leader of\nthe Chicago school of economics who founded monetarism."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Milton Friedman",
        "Friedman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man became President by defeating former Civil War general Benjamin Butler of\nthe Greenback Party and Prohibition candidate John St. John. He edged out his majorparty opponent with a last-minute swing of the (20 pts) ",
        "New York vote, triggered by Samuel\nBurchard denouncing him as the candidate of (10 pts) ",
        "\"rum, Romanism, and rebellion.\" For 10\npoints, name this first post-Civil War Democrat to win the Presidency, who served\nnonconsecutive terms."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Grover Cleveland",
        "Cleveland",
        "Stephen Grover Cleveland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization had a major political effect in 1996, after its weapons master Yahya\nAyyash was killed and it launched a wave of bus bombings. This organization designates its\narmed wing the (20 pts) ",
        "Izzedine al-Qassam (pr. EYE zuh-DEEN ah-kah-SEM) Brigades, and it\ngained popularity by resisting the (10 pts) ",
        "Oslo Accords. For 10 points, name this Islamist group\nwhich opposes the existence of Israel and controls the Gaza Strip."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hamas",
        "Harakat Al-Muqawama Al-Islamia",
        "Islamic Resistance Movement"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Julius von Sachs identified the organelles in which this process takes place. The\nexperiments of Jan Ingenhousz (pr. ING-en-hoos) showed that this process altered the mass\nof the (20 pts) ",
        "organisms involved. Joseph Priestley performed an experiment involving a candle\nand (10 pts) ",
        "mint that showed that this process changes the composition of air. For 10 points, identify\nthis process of plants using light to create sugars from carbon dioxide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "photosynthesis",
        "Calvin cycle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This emperor was the ultimate victor of the Battle of Muhlberg, which suppressed the\nSchmalkaldic (pr. shmal-CALL-dik) League that opposed him. This man's 1525 victory at (20 pts) ",
        "Pavia included the capture of Francis I of France. This father of Philip II summoned (10 pts) ",
        "Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms (pr. VURMZ). For 10 points, name this Hapsburg who\nbriefly united the thrones of Spain and the Holy Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles V",
        "Charles I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) These people were sought out due to the new doctrine of \"limpieza de sangre\" (pr. leempee-EY-zuh day SAHN-gray), or \"cleanliness of blood.\" These people were given a\nderogatory nickname meaning (20 pts) ",
        "\"pig\" and were subject to the public \"auto de fe\" (pr.\nOW-toe deh FAY) if found. Tomas de Torquemada gave these people three months to leave (10 pts) ",
        "Spain in 1492. For 10 points, name these people whom the Inquisition sought to find\nsurvivals of within the \"conversos\" community."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish former Jews",
        "Jew",
        "Jews",
        "secret Jews"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This body was originally under the influence of John Pym and the radical \"Five\nMembers,\" and it was convened to raise money following the Bishops' Wars. This body\nsteadily lost members, ending up named sardonically for Nicholas (20 pts) ",
        "Barebones, after its\nmoderate delegates were removed in Pride's Purge to create the (10 pts) ",
        "Rump Parliament. For 10\npoints, name this Parliament which oversaw the English Civil War and is named because it sat\nfrom 1640 to 1660."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Long Parliament",
        "Long"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man expanded his Keystone Bridge Company into his business empire, which\ngreatly profited from introducing the Bessemer process to widespread use in America. This\nman's 1899 article \"The (20 pts) ",
        "Gospel of Wealth\" outlined his philanthropic plans, which\nincluded founding several (10 pts) ",
        "library systems now named for him. For 10 points, name this\nScottish immigrant who became the greatest steel magnate of the late nineteenth century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Andrew Carnegie",
        "Carnegie"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexey Leonov posits that the training crash which killed this man in 1968 was caused by\nan accidental near-miss with another fighter jet. This man, who was selected out of twenty\ncandidates from (20 pts) ",
        "Star City, whistled the patriotic song \"The Motherland Hears\" while\nre-entering the atmosphere aboard (10 pts) ",
        "Vostok 1. For 10 points, name this Soviet cosmonaut\nwho, in 1961, became the first human to leave the Earth's atmosphere."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yuri Gagarin",
        "Gagarin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 2001 panel of experts in this sport named Regla Torres and Lorenzo Bernardi among\nits three best players of all time. William Morgan invented this game in 1895 as a less\nphysical use of (20 pts) ",
        "basketball courts. Al Scates is the most successful coach in this sport,\nand was the trainer of the generally regarded best-ever player at this sport, (10 pts) ",
        "Karch\nKiraly. For 10 points, name this game in which a libero, blockers, and setters play across an\nelevated net."
      ],
      "answer": "volleyball"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Brooks Henderson was the initial special prosecutor in charge of resolving this\nscandal, but was replaced with James Broadhead after appearing too incorruptible. This\nscandal was organized in St. Louis and involved personal (20 pts) ",
        "secretary Orville Babcock.\nTreasury secretary Benjamin (10 pts) ",
        "Bristow exposed this affair in 1875. For 10 points, name this\nscandal involving the embezzlement of tax revenues on liquor which came to discredit the Grant\nadministration."
      ],
      "answer": "Whiskey Ring"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A road extending from Castrum Truentinum to the Aurelian Walls of Rome was named\nfor this substance, whose transportation was the impetus for building some of the oldest\nknown (20 pts) ",
        "roads. This substance was traded to the north in exchange for gold from the (10 pts) ",
        "African interior, especially by the Ghana empire. For 10 points, identify this formerly valuable\nsubstance which can now be easily retrieved from natural sources such as seawater and is often\niodized."
      ],
      "answer": "salt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man successfully completed the \"red line\" map as part of the plan for a \"Cape to\nCairo railway.\" This man was sent as the agent of the Rothschild company to (20 pts) ",
        "Kimberley, where he spent seventeen years buying competing diamond fields. He founded\nthe (10 pts) ",
        "De Beers company to cement his monopoly over the industry. For 10 points, name this\nBritish colonialist in South Africa who endowed a series of scholarships for foreign students at\nOxford."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cecil Rhodes",
        "Rhodes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Guns fired from this building ended the Battle of the Faubourg St. Antoine (pr. foo-BOO\nsont AHN-twan) during the Fronde. This building is where the Marquis de (20 pts) ",
        "Sade enraged\ncrowds by claiming a plot to massacre its inhabitants. Only seven politically unimportant (10 pts) ",
        "prisoners were found inside when it was stormed on July 14, 1789. For 10 points, name this\nParis prison which was destroyed to start the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "the Bastille"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) In 1595, the Tooth of the Buddha was moved to a reliquary on this island, where the\nKingdom of Kandy long held out against colonization. In the twentieth century, this island\nhad the world's first (20 pts) ",
        "female prime minister, and its (10 pts) ",
        "Sinhalese majority fought a\nprotracted war with a terrorist group that invented suicide bombing. For 10 points, name this\nisland country where the Tamil Tigers fought against the government at Colombo, often spilling\ninto nearby India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "Lanka"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party nominated Atlantis crank Ignatius Donnelly for Vice-President in 1900, eight\nyears after demanding the eight-hour workday and the direct election of Senators in the\nOmaha Platform. This party ran James (20 pts) ",
        "Weaver for President in 1892 and, four years\nlater, insisted on listing Thomas Watson as the running mate of the (10 pts) ",
        "cross-listed\nDemocratic nominee. For 10 points, name this party that peaked in 1896 by endorsing William\nJennings Bryan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Populists",
        "Populist",
        "People's Party",
        "People's"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This bill specifically limited its scope to \"conventional military force\" in order to exclude\nnuclear strikes. This bill was put before the Senate in response to reported attacks on the\nTurner Joy and Maddox. It was opposed by Ernest (20 pts) ",
        "Gruening and Wayne Morse on the\ngrounds of representing a (10 pts) ",
        "conflict \"misguidedly drawn, which is steadily being escalated.\"\nFor 10 points, name this August 1964 Congressional resolution authorizing Lyndon Johnson to\nconduct the Vietnam War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gulf of Tonkin Resolution",
        "Gulf of Tonkin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's colony fought Susquehannock Indians in the Peach War and granted\nreligious freedom in the Flushing Remonstrance. Prior to England, this country sponsored\nthe original American voyages of Henry (20 pts) ",
        "Hudson. This country conquered the shortlived New Sweden colony in present-day Delaware, under the leadership of Peter (10 pts) ",
        "Stuyvesant. For 10 points, name this country which originally colonized what is now New York."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Netherlands",
        "Holland",
        "the Dutch Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This art movement included a literary section in which poets Hugo Ball and Tristan\nTzara worked. Artists in this movement produced \"ready-mades\" such as a bicycle (20 pts) ",
        "wheel and a urinal. This movement's name was supposedly chosen at the Cabaret Voltaire\nby sticking a (10 pts) ",
        "pen-knife into a French dictionary at random. For 10 points, name this\nabsurdist \"anti-art\" movement of the World War I era, which included Marcel Duchamp."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dadaism",
        "Dada"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man collaborated with Morris Halle on the 1968 phonological study The Sound\nPattern of English. That text extended his theory of \"poverty of the (20 pts) ",
        "stimulus,\" or the\ninability of human culture to cause the development of (10 pts) ",
        "language absent a biological role\nin the brain. For 10 points, name this theorist of transformational-generative grammar, an MIT\nlinguist also known for his leadership of the intellectual left wing in the U.S."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Noam Chomsky",
        "Chomsky"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's dictator Hilarión Daza sparked a war by instituting a saltpeter tax,\nleading to this country losing its coastline in the Treaty of Ancón. Both Butch Cassidy and\nChe Guevara were killed in this country, which lost southeastern territory to Paraguay in\nthe (20 pts) ",
        "Chaco War. This country, the site of the Potosí silver mine, is now led by (10 pts) ",
        "coca\nenthusiast Evo Morales. For 10 points, identify this South American country named for the\ncontinent's \"liberator.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Bolivia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a Senate debate which quickly turned into an argument about this crisis, Robert\nHayne received the reply \"liberty and union, one and forever, now and inseparable\" from\nDaniel (20 pts) ",
        "Webster. This crisis was exacerbated by the publication of the South Carolina\nExposition and Protest, and it led to the resignation of Vice-President (10 pts) ",
        "John C. Calhoun.\nFor 10 points, name this 1832 affair in which South Carolina asserted that it could block the\nTariff of Abominations."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "nullification crisis",
        "nullification"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2003, this person was identified as the \"Younger Queen\" mummy by the minority\nfaction of archaeologists which holds that she was the same person as the pharaoh (20 pts) ",
        "Smenkhkare. Berlin's Neues (NOY-iss) Museum currently holds a famous (10 pts) ",
        "bust of this\nperson, which is traditionally attributed to a sculptor known as Thutmose. For 10 points, name\nthis wife of Akhenaten who might have preceded Tutankhamun as pharaoh of Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Nefertiti"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This battle turned on the use of a perpendicular two-column approach, and the few losing\nships that escaped were led by Federico Gravina. Prior to this battle, a (20 pts) ",
        "semaphore\nmessage reading \"England expects that every man will do his duty\" was transmitted from\nthe (10 pts) ",
        "Victory. For 10 points, name this 1805 naval battle at which Pierre-Charles Villeneuve\nwas defeated by Horatio Nelson, who died during the fighting and is commemorated at a\nnamesake London square."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Trafalgar",
        "Trafalgar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The loophole that nothing with \"socially redeeming value\" could meet the definition of\nthis thing led to the former spectacle of brief Shakespeare performances in incongruous\nfilms. Attempts to define this thing led to the Supreme Court cases of Roth v. U.S. and (20 pts) ",
        "Miller v. California. This genre was the subject of Potter Stewart's quote \"I (10 pts) ",
        "know it when\nI see it.\" For 10 points, name this genre which slowly acquired First Amendment protections\ndespite its explicit content."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "pornography",
        "obscenity"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) At the end of this war, the Penghu (pr. PEN-goo) Islands changed hands, as did the\nLiaodong (luh-OW-dong) Peninsula. (20 pts) ",
        "The Port Arthur Massacre occurred during this\nwar, which ended with the transfer of the Pescadores (PESS-cuh-doorz) and Taiwan. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this war ended by the Treaty of Shimonoseki (shim-OH-noh-SEK-ee)\nbetween two Asian powers in 1895."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sino-Japanese War",
        "Sino-Japanese",
        "First Sino-Japanese War",
        "Jiawu War",
        "Jiawu",
        "Japan–Qing War",
        "Japan–Qing"
      ]
    }
  ]
}